<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thanatoktasia. Or, Death disarmed: and the grave swallowed up in victory. A sermon preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, Decemb. 22. 1653. At the publick funerals of Dr. Hill, late Master of Trinity Colledge in that University. With a short account of his life and death. To which are added two sermons more upon the same text, preached afterward in the same place. / By Anthony Tuckney, D.D. Master of St. Johns Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Tuckney, Anthony, 1599-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1523_2</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95353)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 194:E1523[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thanatoktasia. Or, Death disarmed: and the grave swallowed up in victory. A sermon preached at St. Maries in Cambridge, Decemb. 22. 1653. At the publick funerals of Dr. Hill, late Master of Trinity Colledge in that University. With a short account of his life and death. To which are added two sermons more upon the same text, preached afterward in the same place. / By Anthony Tuckney, D.D. Master of St. Johns Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Tuckney, Anthony, 1599-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Rothwel, at the Fountain and Bear in Goldsmiths-row in Cheapside. And S. Gellibrand at the Ball in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition, line 8 on title page reads: "Decemb."; imprint reads "Rothwel" and "Gellibrand".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st XV, 55 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170050:1"/>
            <p>ΘΑΝΑΤΟΚΤΑΣΙΑ. OR, DEATH <hi>DIS ARMED:</hi> And the Grave ſwallowed up in Victory.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at S. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Decemb. 22. 1653. At the publick Funerals of Dr. Hill, Late Maſter of Trinity Colledge in that Univerſity. <hi>With a ſhort account of his Life and Death.</hi> To which are added two Sermons more upon the ſame Text, preached afterward in the ſame place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ANTHONY TUCKNEY, <hi>D. D.</hi> Maſter of <hi>S. Johns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I will ranſome them from the power of the grave, I will redeem them from death: O death, I will be thy plague; O grave, I will be thy deſtruction.</q>
            <bibl>Hoſea 13. 14.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Rothwel,</hi> at the Fountain and Bear in Goldſmiths-row in Cheapſide; And <hi>S. Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand</hi> at the Ball in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170050:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170050:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL my ever honoured Friend, Mr. FRANCIS ASH. Merchant, and Governor of the <hi>Muſcovia Company</hi> of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat I print this Sermon, is not out of any compliance with the ſcribling humour of theſe times, or from the leaſt thought, that by it I ſhall adde any thing to the Argument it treats of, which from other abler mens labours may not be had with better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: But only from the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſome friends, whom I could not well deny, and whoſe aim in it was the glory of God, and the keeping alive the memory of <hi>That</hi> his faithful ſervant at whoſe Funerals it was preach'd.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing that, ſuch as it is, it muſt be Printed, That I dedicate it to <hi>your ſelf,</hi> I have many great cauſes, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you be not, yet I am deſirous that others may take notice of: Amongſt them, I may not, without ingratitude, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your undeſerved reſpects to my ſelf.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170050:3"/>
            <p>But I muſt eſpecially reckon your plain and ſingle-hearted Candor and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, which the painted Pageants of many others now a dayes ſet off with a greater luſter.</p>
            <p>Your cordial love of Gods truth, and of that good old Doctrine <hi>according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to godlineſs,</hi> which thoſe <hi>Worthies of God,</hi> under whom you and I have been trained up, preached, and lived, and died in the belief, practice, and comfort of, to which you do well firmly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here, whilſt too many in this giddy Age are turned aſide to <hi>vain janglings,</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 6 2 Pet. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>pernicious errours;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your fervent zeal for <hi>Chriſts</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry and Miniſters, ſo that whom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſpiſe, you honour; and whom the foot of pride, even of the baſeſt, is ready to tread down and trample upon, your humility and love endevour to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold: Witneſſe that your great, and for many years rarely parallel'd bounty, in giving (and that in your life time) the large ſum of very nigh <hi>three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds per annum,</hi> to moſt pious uſes, <hi>viz.</hi> towards the maintenance</p>
            <p>Of poor Miniſters Widdows.</p>
            <p>Of a Lecture in <hi>London,</hi> the place of your longeſt abode.</p>
            <p>Of two <hi>Schools,</hi> the one in the place
<pb facs="tcp:170050:3"/> of your Birth, and the other of your<note place="margin">Darby, aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>by de l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Zouch.</note> Education.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially of that happy Society of <hi>Emmanuel Colledge</hi> in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, on which you have been pleaſed to confer the greateſt ſhare of it.</p>
            <p>That this plentiful ſhowre of your bounty ſhould be directed to fall on that fruitful <hi>Field,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long hath ſo abundantly <hi>bleſſed,</hi> was his good hand guiding yours to lay it on the head of that fruitful <hi>Ephraim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That your favour to my ſelf ſhould in any meaſure incline your heart to that <hi>Colledge</hi> of which I was then an unworthy Member, was your goodneſse ſo much to honour me. But that which rend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth both <hi>your ſelf,</hi> and <hi>your gift</hi> more highly valued and honoured by All, is</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The greatneſs of it</hi> making <hi>you a ſecond Founder,</hi> at leaſt (after their moſt pious Founder) the greateſt Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor that ever that Colledge had. Like <hi>Solomons Clouds,</hi> which when full<note place="margin">Eccl. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> of rain, empty themſelves abundantly upon the earth; herein you have obeyed Gods command, in <hi>opening your hand</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11. 1 Tim. 6 17. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>wide.</hi> Followed his example, <hi>who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to all richly.</hi> Anſwered has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, who <hi>requireth much where
<pb facs="tcp:170050:4"/> he hath given much.</hi> Ten talents,<note place="margin">Luk. 12. 48. Matth. 25. 20. Deut. 26. 10. &amp; Prov. 3. 9, 10. Math. 25. 24, 25, 26, 27. &amp;c.</note> where he hath given five.</p>
            <p>As Soveraign Lord he will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all. Something he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth from them on whom he hath beſtowed leaſt; but much, on whom more. So that he who in this or the like kind doth nothing, is an <hi>evil ſervant,</hi> a practical <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> thereby in true inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation ſaying, that he hath received nothing: and he who having received much, giveth but little, doth but tell over again <hi>Saphira's</hi> lye in ſaying, <hi>yea, ſo much,</hi> when it was much more, <hi>that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5. 8, 9, 10.</note> made her doom very heavy; whileſt you, whoſe <hi>pound hath gain'd ten pounds</hi> may comfortably expect to hear that bleſſed Euge, <hi>Well done good and</hi>
               <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 19. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>faithful ſervant.</hi> And whatever others may think and ſay, yet if Scripture may be Judge, you have herein done the part of a <hi>good husband:</hi> hereby <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God your debtor,</hi> who being <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 19. 17.</note> will have time enough to ſhew himſelf a <hi>true paymaſter,</hi> and a moſt <hi>plentiful rewarder</hi> of your bounty with his. The prudent husbandman, whatever elſe he is ſparing of, will not ſcant his ſeed-corn; it ſeemeth you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 6. Prov. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> by <hi>ſowing liberally</hi> to <hi>reap libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally;</hi> thus you have done <hi>good to
<pb facs="tcp:170050:4"/> your ſelf,</hi> whileſt you have withal <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Nation,</hi> and the <hi>whole Reformed</hi> Religion. Papiſts boaſt much of their great good works; but ſome of <hi>our Divines</hi> have truly<note place="margin">Dr. Willet,</note> made it out by <hi>Induction</hi> of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that (for their time and ability) <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have equall'd and exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; and let your happy name be added, and in fair letters written in that lovely Catalogue.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>The pious and religious Grounds and ends of giving it;</hi> it was not in way of any Popiſh <hi>penance</hi> to expiate the guilt of ſome fouler crime, which in thoſe blind times built many of their <hi>Churches and Monaſteries,</hi> nor a Legacy bequeathed by the will of ſome cruel oppreſſor, who after that in his life time by his exactions he had made many poor, on his death-bed from ſting of conſcience is enforced to take care for the maintaining of ſome of them, this was no ſuch trucking either with God or man, with the <hi>Papiſt</hi> to merit at <hi>Gods</hi> hands, or with the vain-glorious <hi>Phariſee to blow a Trumpet</hi> to gain<note place="margin">Math. 6. 2. Hoſ. 12. 7. Joh. 2. 14.</note> applauſe with men, which is but to play the <hi>Merchant</hi> and money-changer in the Temple, and in making up their laſt accounts to cloſe up all former op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb facs="tcp:170050:5"/> with a new kinde of uſury; your eye was more ſingle, did not look ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquint, when it looked ſo favourably upon that <hi>Colledge,</hi> but as you were pleaſed to build upon their honourable <hi>Founders</hi> religious foundation, ſo <hi>you both</hi> had the very ſame pious intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He expreſſeth his in the Preface to his ſtatutes in thoſe words, <hi>Pro mea facultate Religionis, &amp; vitae purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad poſteros noſtros propagare,</hi> that according to his ability he might propagate <hi>purity</hi> of life and doctrine to poſterity; from whence ſome great men, and their ſmall friends then at the very firſt thought they ſmelt a <hi>Puritan:</hi> you as clearly manifeſt yours in the words of your Donation to be, <hi>For and towards the furtherance of godlineſs and learning, that ſo the Church of God may be thereby the better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of godly, learned, and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſters.</hi> Bleſſed be God, that <hi>both of you</hi> ſo happily meet in the ſame work, with the ſame heart, and as He in the view of all, hath manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained his end, whileſt that little younger ſiſter hath been as fruitful as any; ſo may <hi>you</hi> alſo yours, in her continuance and encreaſe of yet more fruitfulneſſe anſwerable to Gods wider
<pb facs="tcp:170050:5"/> opening his hand to her, in his and your bounty.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>The time and ſeaſon in which it was given.</hi> This, as it rendreth every thing <hi>beautiful,</hi> ſo it preſents<note place="margin">Eccl. 3. 11 Prov. 2. 5. 11.</note> your rich gift, as <hi>apples of Gold in pictures of Silver:</hi> as a ſmile from heaven, when earth frowned; a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial in a fainting fit. When our <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manack Diviners</hi> could read in the <hi>Heavens</hi> our Miniſtry and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities to be <hi>falling Stars;</hi> and our ABC <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> pretending to more divine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations both in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> could foretell the ſudden ruine of both, and then like a <hi>Jonah</hi> return to their <hi>boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to <hi>ſee what would become of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jonah 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>them;</hi> When <hi>Ignorance</hi> driveled, and madneſse foam'd and rav'd with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted non-ſenſe, and malice plotted our overthrow, and all (Edom-like) cryed <hi>Raſe it, raſe it to the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or rather in<note place="margin">Pſal. 137. 7. Pſal. 46. 1.</note> Scripture-expreſſion <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Then our God from on high <hi>looked through the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of fire upon the hoſt of thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>and took off their Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot-wheels when they drave ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</hi> And then alſo it was that you in your place and rank reached out
<pb facs="tcp:170050:6"/> your able and friendly band to hold and lift us up, when others would have caſt us down; and if he who helpeth to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the weak man at any time doth a friendly office, he who beareth him up when he is now ſtumbling and ready to<note place="margin">Job 12. 5.</note> ſlip, and ſo is as a <hi>deſpiſed lamp,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be trod out as a ſnuffe, doth him a double courteſie: by this God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf commendeth his love to his people, in that he is a <hi>Strength,</hi> but that to the <hi>poor and needy,</hi> and that in <hi>his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 25. 4.</note> a <hi>refuge from the Tempeſt, when the blaſt of the terrible ones is as a ſtorm againſt the wall:</hi> ſuch blaſts we have felt; but bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> and thoſe his ſervants, who have been as<note place="margin">Iſa. 32. 2.</note> 
               <hi>an hiding place from the winde, and a covert from ſuch Tempeſts;</hi> and bleſſed be you alſo who durſt ſet your ſhoulder to uphold a falling wall, and then to appear for us, when ſo many ſo violently oppoſed us; and others who wiſhed us well, could better pitty then help us: a piece not ſo much of <hi>Roman</hi> gallantry, which adventured upon the<note place="margin">Florus l. 2</note> purchaſe of that field in which <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> had pitched his camp, as of true Chriſtian magnanimity, like <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> who in that houre and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkneſs <hi>in extrema deſperatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:170050:6"/> intrepidè in lucem prodiit,</hi> and<note place="margin">Calvin in Joh. 19. 38. Mark. 15. 43.</note> boldly appeared for a crucified Saviour. Let others admire the gay <hi>Tulip,</hi> which will cloſe up when night or a cold blaſt comes; in my eye that is a pleaſant plant that will bloom and bloſſome in an hard Froſt; and that a ſtately bird which will ſwim up againſt the ſtream, while light ſtraws and ſuch traſh are carried down with it.</p>
            <p>In this you have proved your ſelf a true <hi>friend, to love thus at all times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 17.</note> 
               <hi>and more then a brother that is born for adverſity.</hi> Conſtancy in ſuch times when the generality of the world ran a contrary courſe, made <hi>Athanaſius in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ornt. 21. in Laudem Athanaſii.</note> 
               <hi>Nazianzens</hi> eſteem both <hi>Adamas</hi> and <hi>Magnes;</hi> and you in this have proved both; the <hi>Adamant</hi> in your invincible reſolution, notwithſtanding all diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements; and thereby muſt needs prove the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> to draw both ours and all good mens hearts to you. Although therefore they were too bold to tell our Saviour that the <hi>Centurion</hi> was <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to be gratified by him, becauſe he <hi>loved their Nation, and built them a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Synagogue;</hi> Yet you who plead no merit with <hi>God,</hi> are deſervedly worthy to be honoured by men, and ſhall ever be by me, for the like love and bounty. This
<pb facs="tcp:170050:7"/> hath begot you the trouble of this <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and may your peruſal of the book conduce any thing to the guidance of your life, or the comfort of your death, I ſhall account my ſelf to have received a rich reward of this poor labour.</p>
            <p>You read of <hi>Iſaac's</hi> going <hi>out into the field to meditate in the evening;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 24. 63.</note> Sir, it is about that time of the day with you; ſhall you therefore pleaſe in this your evening-walk and meditation, that it may ſometimes bear you company, I hope you and I ſhall have the more cauſe to rejoyce at our laſt moſt comfortable meeting. Now that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> who hath bin the <hi>guide of your youth,</hi> be the ſtaffe of your age, that you may be ſo <hi>planted in his houſe, and flouriſh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>in his Courts,</hi> that you may ſtill bring forth more <hi>fruit in your old age,</hi> and your <hi>fruit may remain</hi> and perpetuate<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 16. Iſa. 56. 5.</note> you a <hi>name better then of ſons and daughters,</hi> which (God enabling me) ſhall be the conſtant and inſtant prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your affectionate friend, very much obliged to love and honour you, ANTHONY TVCKNEY.</signed>
               <dateline>Cambridge, <date>March 27 1654</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170050:7"/>
            <head>DEATH <hi>DISARMED.</hi> AND THE GRAVE Swallowed up in Victory.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON I.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>1 COR. 15. 55.</bibl>
                  <q>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Apoſtle calleth it, <hi>the good fight of faith, 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 12. every way <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>beſt,</hi> becauſe at laſt it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ends <hi>well, in victory,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">1 John 5. 4</note> it <hi>overcomes;</hi> nay, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, proves <hi>more then conquerour</hi> as many other<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 37.</note> wayes, ſo this for one, that as this fight ends in victory, ſo this victory in triumph. For here (otherwiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170050:8"/> then with the <hi>Romans</hi> of old) the Conquerour alwayes triumpheth; and ſo we have this our Conquerour ever and anon brought in trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing, over ſin and miſery, and death it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Over ſin; <hi>Miſerable man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from this body of death? I thank God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Rom.</hi> 7. 24, 25.</p>
               <p>Over all accuſers, and all outward evils<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and enemies; <hi>Who ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach? who ſhall condemn? who ſhall ſeparate? Shall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>nay, I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that none of all theſe, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8. 33, 34. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, over the laſt enemy of all, which is death and the grave; as here in the Text, and following Verſes: <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law;</hi> but <hi>thanks be to God, who giveth us the victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all, obſerve, that it is ſtill <hi>through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170050:8"/> 
                  <hi>through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Happy man that could ſay it! and more bleſſed grace of faith that could prompt and enable him to it! but above all, moſt bleſſed be the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our Salvation, who gave that faith ſuch ſtrength, and thereby this man of God ſuch a conqueſt, that when world and ſin, death and hell had done their worſt, they had done him none, but themſelves all the miſchief, by <hi>bruiſing his heel had broken their own head:</hi> ſo that now as vanquiſhed, and lying proſtrate at his feet; as <hi>Joſhuab</hi> over the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanitiſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24.</note> Kings, or as a little <hi>David</hi> over a great <hi>Goliath,</hi> he treads on<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 51.</note> their necks, trampleth on the Lion and Dragon, without fear of hurt, their teeth being broken, and their ſting taken out, and in this joyful <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, at once</p>
               <p>Both inſulteth over them; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And withal exulteth and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth in God through Chriſt. Now <hi>thanks be to God, who giveth us the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The enemies here triumphed over,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170050:9"/> are <hi>death and the grave,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the latter whereof anſwereth to the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; which if <hi>Del-Rio</hi> will needs have to be alwayes in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adagial: Sacr: in</hi> 2 Sam. 22. <hi>Digreſſ:</hi> 2.</note> Scripture meant of <hi>Hell,</hi> I muſt needs ſay, that I think <hi>Job</hi> was not of his minde, for then he would not have ſo deſired to be hid in it, as he doth, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 13. And therefore the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> when he undertakes to prove that it is ſo underſtood in all the places of Scripture where it is uſed, though he endevour to cleare no fewer then 87 places, did very wiſely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look and leave out this, which (it may be) he could not ſo well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: I grant that you may here finde <hi>Hell</hi> ſet down in the Margin of your Bibles, but its not to be found in the Text, for that <hi>Hell</hi> never loſeth its victory, nor will the prayer, no not of a <hi>Gregory,</hi> though never ſo <hi>great,</hi> (whatever they fable) reſcue any that is once become its priſoner. <hi>Ours</hi> oft tranſlate it <hi>the grave,</hi> and ſo both here and in many other places it muſt be meant: Generally it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>the ſtate of the dead</hi> after their diſſolution: and ſo the latter word may onely hold out a continuation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170050:9"/> of what was in the former: both very near of kinne, and as ſuch you<note place="margin">Cant. 8. 6. Rev. 1. 18. Rev. 6. 8. Rev. 20. 13, 14.</note> have them often in Scripture linked together. In effect, they are the ſame, and ſo the <hi>Vulgar Interpreter</hi> here in ſtead of theſe two words <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Grave,</hi> hath the ſame word <hi>Death</hi> in both clauſes of the Verſe: and beſides, tranſporteth the other words, as <hi>Beza,</hi> and others alſo do,<note place="margin">Junius in Parallelis.</note> who read them thus, <hi>O death, where is thy victory? O grave, where is thy ſting?</hi> Contrary to the <hi>Greek, Syriack,</hi> and <hi>Arabick</hi> Copies, yet in <hi>Beza</hi>'s judgement better ſuiting with the following Verſe, in which I crave leave to diſſent; for I finde the word <hi>ſting</hi> joined to the word <hi>death</hi> there alſo: He might rather have ſaid, that ſo it would be more agreeable to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 14. from which place this Text is taken, with ſome variation of words, (which I now paſſe by) but fully agreeing in the ſame ſenſe. Which is, to repreſent <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> to us in a double, but much different view and poſture.</p>
               <p>1. As an enemy in himſelf armed, and ſo formidable to all, and ſo <hi>death</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170050:10"/> hath its <hi>ſting,</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> hath, or will have the <hi>victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. As the ſame enemy by Chriſt the Captain of our Salvation diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſo to the believer made contemptible, and ſo (as to ſuch) by Jeſus Chriſt, death hath loſt his ſting, and the grave ſhall at laſt be ſwallowed up in victory.</p>
               <p>For that is the true meaning of this queſtion, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> &amp;c. In which the Apoſtle doth not ask, where that was, which they never had, but what they once were poſſeſſed, but now by Chriſt, as to his ſervants, are deſpoiled of. I begin with the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Death (in it ſelf, and as to thoſe</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26. 16.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>thoſe ſons of death who are not reſcued from the power of it) hath its sting, and the grave hath, or will have the victory:</hi> to which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth that proverbial expreſſion, <hi>Cant. 8. 6. Strong as death,</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercometh all, and <hi>cruel as the grave,</hi> which ſpareth none. But more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,</p>
               <p>1. Death hath its ſting: A Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from ſome poiſonous <hi>Serpent,</hi> or <hi>Scorpion,</hi> which with its
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170050:10"/> ſting poiſon's, wound's, kill's, and this ſometimes ſuddenly, unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, irrecoverably.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>death</hi> doth</p>
               <p>1. To the bodily life, as it is the deſtruction of it; and ſo <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> are oppoſed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 15. and if <hi>Hezekiah muſt die, he cannot live, Iſa.</hi> 38. 1.</p>
               <p>And were this all; yet thus, as it is the diſſolution and deſtruction of nature, and the violent parting of ſoul and body, thoſe two long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Plat. Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gias. Ethic. l. 3.</note> and near united friends,</p>
               <p>Even pure nature (and that in our Saviour himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 36, 37, 38, 39.) innocently recoileth from it.</p>
               <p>But to meer natural men, even in the Philoſophers account, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and although ſome of them, whileſt death was at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a Philoſophick bravery, could call them fools that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocl. Aeſchylus Epictetus.</note> of it, and call it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Hermach:</hi> with their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as though not death it ſelf, but only our opinion of it were terrible: yet uſually (as divers of them confeſſe) when after all thoſe vaunts and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170050:11"/> braves, death indeed came neer them, it had a more grim viſage that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted them: and although ſome of them even then either out of brutiſh ſenſleſneſſe, or ſome paſſion of pride, could in a deſperate frolick ruſh upon it as <hi>the horſe doth into the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 8. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>battle;</hi> yet in cooler blood, it was wont to put them into a ſhaking fit, with the great Emperors <hi>pallidula, rigida, nudula;</hi> and if <hi>Epictetus</hi> will except <hi>Socrates,</hi> yet the common rule which obtained with the moſt ſober of them, was, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;<note place="margin">Euripid:</note> the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of truth (I am ſure) ſaith of all ſuch, that <hi>through fear of death, they are all their life time ſubject to bondage, Heb.</hi> 2. 15. And if <hi>life</hi> (as you uſe to ſay) <hi>be ſweet,</hi> it can be no leſſe then the <hi>bitterneſse of death,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 32. <hi>How bitter is the bare</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 41. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>remembrance of it to him that is at eaſe?</hi> but the approach of it was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, bitter bitterneſs, (as the caſe was then with him) even to an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, Iſa.</hi> 38. 17. and if the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of it made him weep, <hi>v.</hi> 3. then<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28. 20.</note> wonder not if <hi>Saul</hi> at it ſwooned quite away.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170050:11"/>
               <p>It is a bitter ſting, that with the<note place="margin">So <hi>Socrates</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Apud Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. Mart. ad Graeces adhortat.</hi> 1.</note> prick of it letteth out the life-blood of the dying man, if when it taketh away from him this life, he hath no aſſurance of a better, but dieth with <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> word in his mouth, <hi>dubius morior, quo vadam neſcio,</hi> be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo wiſe a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, quos nunc abibis in locos?</hi> ſhould he be (with him) never ſo great an <hi>Emperor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not death, as death, that even the godly deſire or rejoice in; for in that ſenſe <hi>Paul</hi> would not be<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 4. Joh. 21. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>unclothed;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> is ſaid in that reſpect <hi>to be carried whither he would not.</hi> It is ſome greater good which God vouchſafeth to ſuch at death, and after it, which whileſt others then want, and have no aſſurance of, it muſt needs be a dolorous and deadly ſting, that thus, firſt letteth out their deareſt life.</p>
               <p>2. And therewith, (which is a ſecond ſtinging wound) all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of life.</p>
               <p>Which ſhould they abide, yet the man is gone, whoſe very ſoul was wrapt up in them, but now hath no benefit by them; and then the ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170050:12"/> room, though never ſo richly hung and furniſhed, is but a ſad ſight, where's nothing elſe to be ſeen but the dead maſter in his coffin in the midſt of it.</p>
               <p>All deareſt <hi>Relations</hi> are at once then ſnapt aſunder.</p>
               <p>The pleaſanteſt <hi>childe</hi> (now half fatherleſſe) turn's away his face, as not being able to endure to ſee a dear <hi>Father</hi> die.</p>
               <p>The deareſt wife, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>deſire of thine eyes,</hi> thou now<note place="margin">Ezek. 24. 16. 21. Gen. 23. 4.</note> deſireſt (with <hi>Abraham) to have buried out of thy ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy moſt loving friends may then ſtand by and weep over thee, but cannot help thee; and at laſt with a <hi>longum vale,</hi> bid thee good night, and ſo part: and doth not this<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth 1. 17</note> ſting?</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Honors</hi> and outward great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Phinehas</hi> his wife now dying, calleth them <hi>Ichabod:</hi> this ſting prick's that ſwoln bladder, and ſo his breath goe's forth, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all his <hi>thoughts,</hi> all his goodly <hi>gliſtering</hi> thoughts, (as that<note place="margin">Pſal. 146. 4</note> word ſeemeth to ſignifie) periſh. Which words hold not forth a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170050:12"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Pope John</hi> the 22. would gather out of them, as though after death his ſoul ſhould ſleep, and think of nothing; but to expreſſe that all his former great high thoughts in his life time, then at death come to nothing.</p>
               <p>For <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and former <hi>facetious</hi> and <hi>jovial merriments;</hi> old <hi>Barzil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19. 35.</note> eyes grow dim in that evening, when he was but now entred within the <hi>ſhadow of death,</hi> but are quite cloſed up in this midnight; in old<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 5.</note> age <hi>deſire faileth,</hi> but in death it is wholly extinct. Death (if nothing do it before) will break many a knot of good fellows: &amp; then adieu ſworn fellow-drunkard, &amp; well if you and I can now come to a good reckoning; and adieu alſo you ſweet Miſtreſs, and all that dalliance you wot of, till you and I ſtand before our Judg, and all that be brought to light which was done by us in ſecret. And adieu to you too my more innocent merry companion, <hi>nec ut ſoles dabis jocos;</hi> the whole club of wits are now all amort, and not one Jeſt more; for now that God and Death are in good earneſt, it is paſt Jeſting, paſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170050:13"/> Drinking, Whoring, yea, rejoicing in wife, or children, or friends:</p>
               <p>Or <hi>Riches,</hi> which ſhould they (as with ſome Nations they are) be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with thee, yet in that <hi>day of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 4</note> 
                  <hi>wrath they will not be able to profit thee;</hi> for if in thy life time they do not (as often they doe) <hi>make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 23. 5</note> 
                  <hi>wings and flee away from thee,</hi> yet in death thou wilt be taken from them; thy cloſe fiſt will be then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and all that duſt which before thou gripedſt in thy hand, will then<note place="margin">See <hi>Shick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> in his <hi>Jus Regiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cap.</hi> 6. Luke 12. 20.</note> run through thy fingers; and then thou fool, <hi>whoſe ſhall all theſe things be?</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Hezekiah!</hi> who in this caſe could ſay of Gods Word and Promiſes, and Providences, <hi>In theſe things is the life of my ſpirit;</hi> but<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 16.</note> the very <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the worldlings <hi>life,</hi> is wrapt up in this bundle of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward contentments: ſo that if that threed be once cut, and ſo all theſe be ſcattered and loſt, then as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid, <hi>What have I more?</hi> the man is<note place="margin">Judg. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> utterly undone, and to whom in time of his life, it was death to part with a penny, it will be an hell at death to part with all; as it was once ſaid by one to a great Lord,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170050:13"/> upon his ſhewing him his ſtately houſe and pleaſant Gardens, Sir, <hi>You had need make ſure of Heaven, or elſe when you die, you will be a very great loſer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is this all; for were it onely the loſſe of life, and outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of it, that ſting <hi>death</hi> faſtneth even in the heirs of <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Thirdly, therefore there is a deeper ſting in it, which the godly are freed from: of which we read in the following Verſe, in theſe words, <hi>The ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the law, ie.</hi> ſin<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 12. <hi>Puncturâ peccati mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimur. P. Martyr.</hi>
                  </note> armeth death with its ſting, which otherwiſe could never have had power to hurt or touch us, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Socinian</hi> ſaith to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and the law now broken doth <hi>ex accidente</hi> irritate, and <hi>per ſe</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and manifeſt, and aggravate ſin, and ſo giveth it its <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and death its warrant thus to arreſt and execute us: and <hi>hinc illae lachrymae,</hi> hence is the deepeſt ſting of death, and deadlieſt groan of the dying ſinner; for that with death, the weight both of ſin and the law fall on him together, which preſſeth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170050:14"/> him yet lower, and woundeth him deeper even to the ſoul and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whileſt he is hereby made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that his death is the <hi>wages of his ſin,</hi> ſo that he dieth not as a<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23</note> 
                  <hi>Martyr,</hi> or barely as a <hi>Man,</hi> but as a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> under the guilt of ſin, and ſenſe of Gods wrath; and if there was a painful <hi>ſting</hi> of death in the two former particulars, then in this third is the very <hi>poiſon</hi> of it. <hi>That,</hi> as the ſting of a Bee may be very painful, but <hi>This is</hi> the Hornet and Scorpion: This Scorpions ſting in the tail (as thoſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 10.) in the end of our life is moſt deadly; as they uſe to ſay, <hi>Maximè mortiferi morſus beſtiarum morientium,</hi> the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a dying beaſt is moſt deadly, the ſting of death, if dipt in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome of Gods wrath, is both into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable and incurable. That <hi>facies Hypocratica,</hi> (which <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſpeak of) of a ſpent dying man looks very ghaſtly; but no ſight in all the world more dreadful, than to ſee an awakened dying ſinner (as a <hi>Saul, Judas, Francis Spira,</hi> &amp;c.) conflicting with death, and ſin, and the law, and Gods curſe, and wrath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170050:14"/> altogether. If in a dying houre, in ſtead of Gods reviving <hi>ſmile,</hi> the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner meeteth with his deadly <hi>frown,</hi> ſo that when death hath made his grave, his ſin like a maſſie grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone<note place="margin">Iſa. 24. 20.</note> lie heavy upon him, how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably is that poor wretch <hi>preſſed to death?</hi> and how deadly is that groan when you may hear him ſighing out his ſoul with this ſaddeſt mone; Oh! I am ſo ſick, that I cannot live, and yet (woful wretch that I am!)<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Harris.</hi>
                  </note> ſo ſinful that I dare not die? Oh that I might live! Oh that I might die! O that I might doe neither! <hi>At non ſic abibunt odia,</hi> Friend, you ſhall doe both: becauſe you are a ſinner, you muſt die; but becauſe you die in your ſin, you ſhall live in torment to eternity.</p>
               <p>4. For that is the laſt and worſt ſting of death, which thruſts the ſword in to the hilts; that it is ſuch a ſting, <hi>quo mortales ex hac vitâ</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Del-Rio Adag: pag. 250.</note> 
                  <hi>expellens ad mortem ſecundam exſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulat,</hi> that this firſt death when come, (if better care be not before taken) will prick us on, and thruſt us into a ſecond; for ſo was the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the firſt ſentence, <hi>In dying,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170050:15"/> thou ſhalt die.</hi> So that one death<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> leadeth on to another; the <hi>firſt</hi> to the <hi>ſecond,</hi> that whatever it be which the unpardoned ſinner ſuffereth in the firſt death, it is but the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 24. 8. Deut. 32. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>of ſorrowes;</hi> the fire now kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led will <hi>burn to the loweſt hell:</hi> for ſo we read of death mounted <hi>on his pale horſe, and hell following him, Rev.</hi> 6: 8. (and that was in the time of the<note place="margin">See <hi>C. à Lapide in</hi> Hoſ. 13. 14</note> Goſpel, and not onely of the Law) that <hi>after death cometh judgement, Heb.</hi> 7. 29. and that when the body <hi>returneth to the duſt,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7. if not to him as a <hi>Father,</hi> to be received into his boſome, then as to a <hi>Judge,</hi> to receive its everlaſting doom: and if (as the Apoſtle ſaith) the Devil hath the <hi>power of death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Targum, habet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium mortis.</hi> Grotius.</note> you may eaſily gather that with ſome, death and hell are not farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder; and although he helped the <hi>Heathen,</hi> to put out of their mindes the dreadfulneſſe of it, by the dream of their <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields, as he doth the <hi>Turks</hi> now by that of their <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> yet to an awakened ſinner, now at the point of death, to bee but in danger of it, as not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170050:15"/> knowing whither he ſhall go, leaveth him at a woful loſſe; but if (as they ſay of the <hi>Molle</hi>) he hath then firſt his eyes open, and ſo cometh to ſee himſelf now on the brow of the the hill, and from that precipice now certainly falling into the lake of fire and brimſtone, he giveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf utterly loſt for ever. And thus in all theſe four reſpects, we ſee <hi>that death hath his ſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. And <hi>Hades,</hi> or the <hi>grave, hath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Prov. 30. 15. 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. 5. 24. 2 Kings 2. 11. 1 Cor. 15. 51. <hi>Immutatio illa ſpecies mortis erit.</hi> Beza <hi>in</hi> Heb. 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>or will have the victory;</hi> it being that open Sepulchre, which ſtill crieth, <hi>Give, Give,</hi> till it have ſwallowed up all; for it is <hi>appointed</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>for all men once to die, Heb.</hi> 9. 27. even <hi>Enochs</hi> and <hi>Elijahs</hi> aſſumption, and the change of thoſe, who ſhall be found alive at the laſt day, being a kinde of death, and an analogicall diſſolution: ſo that death having one age after another (as it were) <hi>mowed</hi> down the whole field of the world, and as <hi>a laſt enemy,</hi> having conquered all the great Conquerors of the earth, and with them vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all elſe; and ſtill keeping the field, will have thereby obtained a complete victorie.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170050:16"/>
               <p>1. In thus bringing down all.</p>
               <p>2. So as never to have riſen more, as ſome conceive, had it not been for Chriſt, who as he is the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Life, <hi>John</hi> 11. 25. ſo by him onely (either as <hi>Head</hi> or <hi>Judge</hi>) is the reſurrection from the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21.</p>
               <p>3. And yet further, ſo as that the moſt of them that riſe again, ſhall preſently ſink down again into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death: and ſo this <hi>ſting</hi> prove's that <hi>worm</hi> which <hi>never dieth,</hi> where the fire never <hi>goeth out, Mark</hi> 9. 48.<note place="margin">Igne quaſi ſalietur; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Brugen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Myrothec in <hi>John</hi> 3. 36.</note> but where, the <hi>ſacrifice is ſalted with fire,</hi> ver. 49. burn's but conſume's not; fire being of a burning, but ſalt of a preſerving nature. <hi>Perdit ſed non diſperdit, &amp; cruciat ita ut nunquam perimat,</hi> as <hi>Camero</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where expreſſeth it: So that to them the <hi>Greek</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, will anſwer the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it will be both in <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriam,</hi> and in <hi>perpetuum,</hi> and ſo a <hi>ſignal</hi> and a final victory.</p>
               <p>Now confider this, ye that forget <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 50. 22. 1 King. 14. 6.</note> God; for as the Prophet ſaid to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> wife, <hi>I am ſent to you with heavy tidings this day;</hi> if there be ſuch a four-forked ſting in death, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170050:16"/> we have ſeen in the former particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; then to you, who are not as yet made <hi>partakers of the grace of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>life,</hi> here is matter of 1. Fear. 2 Care.</p>
               <p>Firſt, of Fear: and O that the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> conſideration of this ſting might now prick your hearts kindly, that the ſting it ſelf may not at laſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wound them: <hi>Seneca</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ſurly Stoical Principle, would perſwade himſelf and others, that <hi>it is ill to deſire death, but worſe to fear it.</hi> But the Word of God teacheth us, that ſuch as they, have no cauſe to deſire it, but great cauſe heartily to fear it; and that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their fear of it, they are all <hi>their life time ſubject to bondage.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 15.</note> Whence it is, that</p>
               <p>1. In their health and life they cannot endure (their thoughts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fears) ſeriouſly to think of it. Like them, <hi>who put far away the evil</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 6. 3, 4, 5. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>day;</hi> and for that purpoſe, <hi>chaunted to the ſound of the viol, and drunk wine in bowles,</hi> to ſing and drink a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſuch heart-qualms, as <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11. who charged all about him not to name the terrible name of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170050:17"/> death to him; and muſt not that then be a terrible ſight, which a ſtout man dare not look on?</p>
               <p>2. In their ſickneſſe, when death now approacheth; if their eyes be but open, they are horribly affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at it. <hi>Paſhur</hi> is then a <hi>Magor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſabib. Saul</hi> though a King, and<note place="margin">Jer. 10. 3.</note> valiant, at the news of it, falleth all along <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quantus quantus erat,</hi> as <hi>P. Martyr</hi> rendreth<note place="margin">1 Sam. 28. 20.</note> it; and the taller he was, the heavier was his fall. <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> a mighty<note place="margin">Dan. 5. 1, 2 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> Emperour, and now in the height of his jollity, upon the like occaſion is ſtruck all amort, <hi>his countenance is changed, his thoughts trouble him, the joints of his loins are looſed, and his things ſmite one againſt the other:</hi> But what is the matter, that caſts him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſhaking fit, and trembling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment? It was onely the <hi>fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a mans hand,</hi> writing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing<note place="margin">ver. 5.</note> on the wall; and that, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he could not read, and ſo underſtood not; and why then ſhould he be ſo amazed at it? Alas! he feared that it was (as indeed it proved) a Letter written to him from him, whom <hi>Bildad</hi> calleth the <hi>King of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 18. 14.</note>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170050:17"/> 
                  <hi>terrors,</hi> &amp; that was it w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſo terrified him: for ſo we read the in Scripture,</p>
               <p>Of the ſhadow of death, as a very gloomy thing, <hi>Job 10. 21, 22. ca.</hi> 16. 16. and 24. 17.</p>
               <p>Of the meſſengers of death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
               <p>Of the ſnares, ſorrowes, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of death, <hi>Pſal. 18. 4, 5. Pſal.</hi> 55. 4. as moſt terrible; and indeed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them all that which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rhet. l. 1. c. 6.</note> mentioneth in the proper object of fear.</p>
               <p>1. It is evil; and the evil of it in the former particulars, we have ſeen was very great.</p>
               <p>2. And this near at hand; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>He</hi> inſtanceth in this very particular of Death, and ſaith, that becauſe we think it farre off, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we do not fear it: yet at all times (for any thing that we know) it may be near enough; and now to the dying man its very near, <hi>even at the doores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. And (which according to his rule, maketh all terrible things the<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> more terrible) it is irrecoverable; if not then well done, can never be mended, and ſo the man is utterly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170050:18"/> undone for ever; and this can be no leſſe, then of all <hi>terribles the moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.</hi> For with what a trembling hand, and aking heart, doth the ſick man take that potion, which he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knowe's will either <hi>mend</hi> him, or <hi>end</hi> him? but with how much greater horrour and amazement, muſt that ſinner needs taſte of death's cup, who knoweth that it will doe neither? Neither <hi>mend</hi> him, no, nor yet <hi>end</hi> him, onely end his former enjoyments, but begin his endleſſe torments. Could then the moſt careleſſe and obſtinate ſinner be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to ſit down, and but for one hour, and in good earneſt ſadly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think himſelf thus: <hi>This day and hour I may die, and then not onely all the delights of ſin and the world, which I have hitherto taken up with, at one clap are gone for ever: but I have then an incenſed Judge to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, an irreverſible ſentence and doom to be then paſſed upon me, and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt torments to be endured by me, and thoſe never to end, when my life and all the comforts of it are ended, but after millions of millions of years, yet (as it were) to begin ſtill, and all this (for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170050:18"/> any thing that I can be ſure of to the contrary) may begin with me this day, this hour, this moment.</hi> Were this, in his more ſecret retirement (when the hot fit of a wantons luſt is a little coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the drunkards wine evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and the good fellows cloſet door ſhut, and he withdrawn from the noiſe of his ranting compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſcience ſuffer'd in this ſelf-parly to ſpeak out freely:) were this, <hi>I ſay,</hi> but ſeriouſly thought on, and ſadly laid to heart, were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that he ſhould deſperately goe on in his ſin, and thus madly <hi>kick</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 9. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt theſe pricks,</hi> againſt this ſting of death, ſo ſharp, and ſo deadly? Thou, who (it may be) with <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 16.</note> canſt not endure to ſee another die, how wil thy heart die quite away within thee (as <hi>Nabals</hi> did) when<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 37.</note> thou ſeeſt thine own death approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? If the ſtingings of <hi>Bees</hi> and <hi>Waſps</hi> be ſo painful, how deadly will the ſting of death be to thee? Miſerable would that mans death be, who ſhould bee buried alive in a Vault, full of Serpents and Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Friend, thou art the man,</hi> and unleſſe betimes thou look better to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170050:19"/> it, ſuch will thine be, thou <hi>wilt be ſtung to death.</hi> And whatever they ſtory of <hi>Exagon,</hi> who was caſt into a<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 28. c. 3.</note> great veſſel of Serpents, which (<hi>they ſay) circummulcentibus linguis,</hi> did gently lick him, and not ſting him: yet no <hi>Pſylli,</hi> or <hi>Marſi,</hi> or <hi>Ophiogenes,</hi> are armour of proof againſt the ſting of death, but it will ſting deadly.</p>
               <p>How vain therefore and deſperate is the courſe of ſuch, who in ſtead of fearing death,</p>
               <p>1. Out of grief, fear, diſcontent, or deſpondency and deſpair, being<note place="margin">Job 3. 1 Kings 19 4. Jer. 20. 14, 15, &amp;c. Jonah 4. 8 1 Sam. 31. 4. 2 Sam. 17. 23. Matt. 27. 5</note> weary of life, either wiſh or procure their own death? We read of <hi>Job, Elijah, Jeremiah, Jonah,</hi> faulty in the former, and <hi>Saul, Ahitophel, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> and many in our times, have been ſad inſtances of the latter. But O wofull deluſion! as though death had not a more deadly ſting then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which in this life they can feel or fear. This is then but <hi>è fumo in flammam,</hi> as <hi>the mans flying from a Lion, and a more ſavage Bear meet's him, or going from it into the houſe,</hi> (that houſe, <hi>Job</hi> 30. 23.) and this more venemous Serpent there <hi>bites him, Amos</hi> 5. 19.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170050:19"/>
               <p>2. Or out of a brutiſh ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity and blockiſhneſſe, harden themſelves againſt it. I ſay, <hi>brutiſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exercit. 307. diſt. 33.</note> becauſe as <hi>Scaliger</hi> well obſerveth, Death being a privation, and ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcernable by underſtanding. <hi>Brutes</hi> becauſe they doe not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, do not therefore rationally fear it; and ſo proportionably the more brutiſh men are, the leſſe thoughts and fears they have of death uſually. But notwithſtanding the <hi>Leviathans</hi> ſcales are otherwiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penetrable, yet he <hi>that made him, can make his ſword approach unto him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 40. 18, 19</note> Deaths ſting can pierce ſuch armour, even to the quick through ſuch a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous brawnyneſſe. The great block, though it do not ſo ſoon take fire, yet when throughly kindled, burn's more fiercely.</p>
               <p>3. Or for ſome outward profit and advantage, or popular applauſe daringly adventure upon it;</p>
               <p>As <hi>Theeves</hi> and <hi>Robbers</hi> doe, to<note place="margin">Prov. 1. 13. 19.</note> maintain a ſharking life; yea, and thoſe braver ſparks in former and latter warres, if it be (not for God and their Countrey, in a good cauſe, way, intention, but) that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170050:20"/> they may goe out in the blaze of a proud affectation of bravery and renown. But <hi>Solomon</hi> though (it may be) not ſo ſtout and hardy a Souldier, yet a far wiſer man, may<note place="margin">See <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> and <hi>Baynus in locum.</hi> Prov. 21. 6</note> aſſure them, and that from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, that ſuch rufflings and bravery are <hi>but a vanity toſsed to and fro of them that ſeek death.</hi> It is an undoing gain to break their arm by catching at a feather, to loſe their precious lives and ſouls for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſpoils, a <hi>vanity toſſed</hi> to and fro, like ſtraws and feathers, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their bodies, ſoules, eſtate, name, poſterity, they are the better for, but in all every way the worſe, which will therefore appear to have been a very bad bargain at their laſt reckoning: as it will alſo be found by thoſe other, who account it their gallantry readily and chearfully to breathe their laſt, if thereby they may gain the vain breath of popular applauſe: too great a price for ſo mean a purchaſe; and too daring a brave, if they would conſider that deaths ſting is ſharper then their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſword point. Such ſhould firſt<note place="margin">Suetonius in Nero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> with <hi>Nero</hi> feel the point of the pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170050:20"/> before they ſtab themſelves with it, and get themſelves more fit for death, and this ſting of it taken out before they thus fool-hardily venture upon it, otherwiſe what was ſaid then to <hi>Nero, uſque adeone mori miſorum eſt?</hi> was but cool comfort to his fainting heart in that agony.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>So</hi> Tacitus <hi>of</hi> Vitellius, praeterita, inſtantia, futura par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> oblivione dimiſerat, mirum apud ipſum de bello filentium &amp; prohibit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> per levita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Pſal. 90. 12</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>4. There is a fourth ſort of men not ſo daring as the former, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way as ſecure, who yet are moſt heartily afraid of it, but therefore labour to put away all thoughts of it, their habitually being afraid, puts them upon all means by which they may prevent and baniſh all actuall fears; and ſo they feaſt <hi>without fear,</hi> Jud. 12. Tell over their caſh, that they may not be troubled with <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring their dayes.</hi> Lye down and ſleep on their heaps, and then dream of goods <hi>laid up for man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ears,</hi> Lu. 12. 19. and of Lands and Houſes <hi>to endure to all generations,</hi> Pſal. 49. 11. But is it the way to overcome an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to get as farre as we can from him, or never to think of him? or by ſhutting my eyes, to keep the Bees from ſtinging me? Although theſe men ſleep, yet their <hi>judgement
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170050:21"/> ſlumbreth not.</hi> Death mean while<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3.</note> maketh his approaches, and ſo is upon them before they are aware, and then <hi>their covenant with death is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anull'd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>and their agreement with hell will not ſtand;</hi> then <hi>thou fool, this night,</hi> is a <hi>dreadful ſound in their eares, when in his proſperity, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 15. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>cometh upon him;</hi> when it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the dead of the night, when they ſlept ſo ſecurely, and never<note place="margin">Exod. 12. 29, 30.</note> dream't of it: as <hi>Egypts</hi> cry for their dead at midnight was very dreadful; and <hi>Laiſh</hi> is ſo much the<note place="margin">Jude 18.</note> more affrighted at ſuch an enemies approach, by how much further off ſhe was from thoughts of him; but how much more comfortable and happy would it be to prevent thoſe after ſinking terrors of <hi>death,</hi> by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent more ſafe and ſaving feares of it?</p>
               <p>An anſwerable care to prepare <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 7.</note> for it, as <hi>Noah moved with fear pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared an Ark;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> feare ſhould ſtand <hi>Sentinel,</hi> is the <hi>conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and <hi>watchful</hi> affection, as the fearful <hi>Hare</hi> ſleepeth (they ſay) with her eyes open. O that ours could
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170050:21"/> ſo look about us, that (ſeeing thoſe of us that are young may die ſoon; and they that are old cannot live long; the ripe apple will drop down of it ſelf, and the green may be ſoon pluckt or ſhaken down) that when (it may be) on the ſudden we are gotten into the gloomy ſhadow of death, our <hi>feet may not ſtumble on</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 13. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>thoſe dark mountains;</hi> but that when our death cometh, we may be found in ſuch an eſtate, frame of ſpirit, and way of life, that our hearts may not then die, when our bodies doe, but that upon better ground we may uſe <hi>Cheraeae's</hi> words. <hi>Nunc tempus proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto eſt, cum perpeti me poſſim interfici.</hi> I thank God I dare die; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ſee I muſt now die either a natural or a violent death, yet (I bleſſe him) I can ſay with <hi>Steph:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mylii A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poph.</hi> pag. 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Brunus</hi> the Martyr, <hi>Mors ſanè mihi terribilis non eſt,</hi> death though it look grim on me, is not terrible to me, and with <hi>Ambroſe; I have not ſo lived, as that either I am aſhamed to live, or afraid to die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was a great word of <hi>Lucan's,</hi> which he ſaid of the <hi>Gauls</hi> and <hi>Britans: animaeque capaces mortis,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170050:22"/> and this becauſe they believed the immortality of the ſoul, happy ſhould we be, if upon a better account, it might be ſaid of us <hi>Britains,</hi> that becauſe Chriſt hath <hi>brought life and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>immortality to light by the Goſpel,</hi> and hath by his death taken out the ſting of ours, that therefore we are indeed <hi>capaces mortis,</hi> we <hi>dare die,</hi> and in<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſa. 22. 26.</note> death it ſelf, <hi>our hearts can live.</hi> Sweet bird that can ſing ſo ſweetly and pleaſantly, and that in winter!</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But how may this <hi>Nightingale</hi> thus ſing; with this thorn (this ſting of death) at her breaſt? what are we to do in the time of our life, that when death cometh, this ſting of it may not hurt us?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> in his Books up and down telleth us of many things, which either prevent or cure the ſtingings of Bees and Serpents, and you meet with them almoſt in every page of your ordinary <hi>Herbaliſts:</hi> but when you have read and known all them, you muſt ſeek and ſearch for reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt the ſting of death in more ſacred Volumes. The <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> (I confeſs) in their writings, have in their kinde many excellent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170050:22"/> meditations of death, and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it. Speak much and high of an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> too: but after all that, death is like that <hi>deaf adder,</hi> that <hi>hear's not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the voice of ſuch charmers, though they charm</hi> (at leaſt as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and too many now amongſt us think) very <hi>wiſely:</hi> this leſſon is learnt to purpoſe onely in the ſchool of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> whoſe blood alone take's out this ſting, and cure's the wounds made by it, whileſt miſerable <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and of no value</hi> are they all, ſith<note place="margin">Job 13. 4.</note> all their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are but as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which help to ſtupifie the part affected, and to make it ſenſleſſe (which <hi>Mountebanks</hi> eaſily can doe) rather then to work any perfect cure: And therefore <hi>Ficin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> preſcribes a better <hi>method of Phyſick,</hi> who after his <hi>Tracts, de Sanitate tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda,</hi> and then <hi>de Sanitate reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda,</hi> and <hi>de vita producenda,</hi> becauſe after all thoſe courſes gone through, death will not at laſt be put off, and if better courſe be not taken, when it cometh, will bring its ſting with it; he wiſely addeth another <hi>Tract de vita coeleſti comparanda,</hi> to ſhew
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170050:23"/> how when at death we can live no longer here, we may then live with God in Heaven for ever: which is only by Chriſt, who alone can then make us happy, and our deaths comfortable: what therefore the <hi>Poets</hi> fable of <hi>Perſius</hi> his borrowing of armour from ſeveral of their <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> to harneſs him againſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with <hi>Meduſa:</hi> may direct and<note place="margin">See <hi>Bacons Augm.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 13. p. 137.</note> quicken our diligence and carefulleſt endevour to get that from the true <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which may compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arm and ſecure us againſt this our laſt enemies deadly ſting.</p>
               <p>Many are the precepts of the <note n="*" place="margin">De Arte moriendi. Perkins, Bellarmin, I. Beuſt. M. Cyrus, Mi. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus.</note> 
                  <hi>Art of dying well,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> calls it, which he and other Chriſtian wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters afford us, to whom I muſt for the preſent refer you, and all that I ſhall now ſay, is,</p>
               <p>That in the <hi>general, ſomething,</hi> nay, <hi>much,</hi> nay, <hi>all</hi> is to be done in this time of our life, that we may not meet with this ſting in death: nor will it be done with a <hi>Baalams</hi> wiſh that he <hi>might die the death of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 23. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>righteous:</hi> as <hi>Euchrites</hi> (who in this did not make good his name) would be <hi>Craeſus vivens,</hi> and <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170050:23"/> mortuus;</hi> but he who would die<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 8.</note> comfortably, muſt live holily: we <hi>muſt live to the Lord, if ever we would</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>die in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in particular, would we not have our death too ſtingy, and its ſting deadly: many are the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are held forth to us by the Scriptures, and from them by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chriſtian writers, ſome of which I ſhall touch upon in the application of the ſecond Doctrine, which is, that</p>
               <p>The ſting of <hi>death,</hi> and the victory <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> of the <hi>grave</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt is taken away as to true believers, who may with <hi>Paul</hi> triumph over both, as the Apoſtle both in his own and their name doth here in the Text, <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory?</hi> A moſt bleſſed and comfortable Goſpel-Truth, mainly intended in the Text, and was by me to have been now treated upon in my firſt choice of it, as beſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the preſent occaſion; but an ill-made pen makes double let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; mine was ſuch, and ſo inſtead of one, wrote two Sermons: the latter though more comfortable, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170050:24"/> better agreeing with our preſent bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, yet may be now the better ſpared, becauſe all that I ſhould have ſaid in the proſecution of it, is ſo fully exemplified in the life and death of our lately deceaſed reverend and dear brother Dr. <hi>Thomas Hill,</hi> late Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge, and a moſt uſeful and happy prime mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this our Univerſity, whoſe<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrington</hi> the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator</hi> at St. <hi>Maries,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar,</hi> one of the <hi>ſenior</hi> Fellows of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in their Hall. <hi>Camero. Myrothre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iu</hi> Luk. 11. 47, 48. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Talm. Hieroſol.</hi>
                  </note> ſad Funerals we now celebrate.</p>
               <p>Concerning whom, if any <hi>Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick</hi> be expected of his deſerved praiſes, that will by and by be better performed by them whoſe work it is. But as for him, I believe that he was not ambitious with <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> to go off the ſtage with a <hi>Plaudite;</hi> ſo for my part, I came not up hither to paint Sepulchers, when the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and adorning, even of thoſe of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> with our Saviour had no favourable conſtruction.</p>
               <p>The Jewes have a ſaying, that <hi>non facienda ſunt monumenta juſtis,</hi> whoſe words and works are their beſt <hi>monuments,</hi> and which praiſe the <hi>righteous man,</hi> as well as the <hi>vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman in the Gates, Prov.</hi> 31. 31. And truly, if when wee have done
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170050:24"/> well, to hear ill, be a royalty; then<note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è agere, &amp; male audire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium eſt.</note> much more after a life well led (whether we be rich or poor) to have no more ſaid of us then was of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that <hi>the poor man died, and was carried by the Angels into Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 16. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>boſome.</hi> I ſhall ever judge to be a very large Funeral <hi>Encomium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet when I read of all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> doing <hi>Hez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 32, 33. Act. 9. 39.</note> honour at his death, and of the <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows weeping, and ſhewing the coats which</hi> Dorcas <hi>made while ſhe was with them,</hi> I am not ſo ſtrait-laced or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, as when any mans life hath been eminently remarkable and exemplary, leſt I ſhould be guilty of idolatry in adoring him, to commit ſacriledge, in robbing both the dead of his juſt praiſe, and the living of an uſeful pattern for their imitation.</p>
               <p>That this our <hi>Brother</hi> was ſuch an one, is ſo generally known to you all, and more fully to my ſelf by 34 years experience and acquaintance, that I am the more ſecure, that what I ſhall ſay of him, will be leſs ſuſpected of flattery or falſhood.</p>
               <p>He was born at <hi>Knighton</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire,</hi> of godly Parents, (and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170050:25"/> 
                  <hi>David</hi> accounteth it his great honor<note place="margin">Pſal. 86. 16</note> and bleſſing to be the Son of Gods <hi>Hand-maid:</hi>) both yet alive, and they happy in ſo bleſſed a Son, and although juſtly ſad that he died ſo ſoon, yet ſo as that they may chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bleſſe God, that he lived ſo long, to do ſo much good in his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
               <p>As they dedicated him to God, ſo in order thereto, they trained him up to School-learning in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and when he was fit, they ſent him for further ripening to <hi>Emanuel</hi> Colledge in this Univerſity: where the Roſe was not cankered in the bud, his youth not corrupted and debauched, as with grief wee have ſeen many ſo tainted and poiſoned, that they have been irrecoverably undone themſelves, and have alſo infected others. But this morning (like that 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 4.) was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out clouds, not ſullied with any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted miſcarriage, that I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; but on the contrary, as it is ſaid of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when young, that<note place="margin">Judg. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit of the Lord began then to move him:</hi> ſo in his then ſober and ſtudious behaviour, the Sun looked
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170050:25"/> out betime in that Summer morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and through grace (otherwiſe then it oft falls out in nature) gave promiſing hopes of an after clearer day.</p>
               <p>This was taken notice of by the <hi>Governours of the Colledge,</hi> who thereupon choſe him <hi>Scholar of the Houſe,</hi> hee (as his <hi>Saviour</hi>) ſtill<note place="margin">Luke 2. 52 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Plato in Theag.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>growing in wiſdom and ſtature, and in favour both with God and man.</hi> O that young ſcholars in that <hi>vigorous,</hi> but yet <hi>dangerous</hi> age of theirs, would look on ſuch patterns, and go, and do likewiſe.</p>
               <p>Some good time for his further perfecting, and the more happy ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of his ſpirit, hee ſpent with that man of God, now alſo with God, Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire;</hi> where, upon Gods rich bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his moſt godly directions and example, and the ſociety he had with him, and other eminent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians there, he was much improved and furthered, as otherwiſe, ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially heaven-way, which moſt happily went along with him to his Journies end.</p>
               <p>Upon his return from thence to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170050:26"/> the Colledge, it was not long before he was choſen <hi>Fellow,</hi> with general ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, though upon a moſt ſtrict &amp; double <hi>examen,</hi> more (I think) then ever was in that Colledge before, or hath been ſince, though it ſtill is, and ever hath been according to the <hi>Statutes</hi> very ſtrict and ſerious, and which hath been bleſt to be a ſpecial means of holding up true worth and learning in that happy Society.</p>
               <p>And now, through Gods good hand, leading and ſtrengthening him, he proves a diligent and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſeful <hi>Tutor</hi> of very many <hi>Pupils,</hi> and divers of them of quality, who have proved great bleſſings, both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> And thus, as he was before a pattern for <hi>young Scholars:</hi> ſo in this, of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> great is the truſt, which <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> the whole <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> above all puts in them; and great may be the bleſſing, which upon their faithfulneſſe, may come by them; whileſt ſo many <hi>Townes, Congregations, Countreys,</hi> are bleſſed with ſo many good <hi>Magiſtrates, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and <hi>School-maſters,</hi> as they have had Pupils, whom they have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170050:26"/> been means of doing good to. No one part of their lives (I believe) is of more conſequence, or may be of more ſervice, or will come to a more ſtrict account at their laſt great rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning. And therefore I both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and hope their care will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, eſpecially now, when, as they have more liberty to be, and to do as much good as they will; ſo there will not be wanting ſuch as will be very ready to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from the miſcarriage either of our ſelves, or of them that are under our charge, to ruine all.</p>
               <p>But this our wiſe <hi>Maſter-Builder</hi> ſatisfied not himſelf, as a <hi>Tutor</hi> in poliſhing of <hi>Builders,</hi> but as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and painful <hi>Miniſter,</hi> he labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly endevoured to ſquare other <hi>lively ſtones</hi> for Gods Temple; and<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 5.</note> ſo as he read to <hi>Scholars</hi> in the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> ſo he diligently and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably Preached to a neighbour-<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Andrews</hi>
                  </note> in the <hi>Town.</hi> Which, I believe, many poor ſouls doe to this day bleſſe God and him for.</p>
               <p>Nor was he an <hi>hireling, to flie when the Wolf came;</hi> but when the<note place="margin">John 10. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>plague</hi> in this time of his Miniſtery
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170050:27"/> raged in the Town, he then conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with them in the work. The better Shepherd he, that not onely<note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 4. 16.</note> fed the ſound, but alſo healed and bound up the torn and weak of the flock. This I am ſure in all unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes afterward taken by ſome, ſhould not have been forgotten.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Alabaſter</hi> box of precious ointment thus poured out, <hi>filled the whole houſe with its odour,</hi> and the<note place="margin">John 12. 3</note> ſweet fragrancy of it ſpreadeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, ſo that now he come's to be more taken notice of by many both great and good men, and ſo by ſome of eminent worth and honour, hee was called to the Paſtoral charge of <hi>Tichmerſh</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> where he laboured faithfully in Gods Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt about eight or nine years, and partly by Preaching and converſing up and down with others; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially (otherwiſe then our <hi>Erratick Itineraries</hi> uſe is) with his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial charge, he proved a great bleſſing not onely to that Town, but alſo to the whole Countrey: like another <hi>Bernard Gilpin,</hi> in every<note place="margin">See his life written by Biſhop <hi>Carlton.</hi>
                  </note> place where he came, ſpreading a good ſavour, and leaving it behinde him.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170050:27"/>
               <p>Whileſt he was thus at his work there, for more publick ſervice hee was choſen by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for one of that <hi>County,</hi> to attend and aſſiſt in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together by their Authority: where being of very good uſe, hee was often <hi>Ordered</hi> by the Parliament to Preach before them at their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Faſts,</hi> and upon other their more ſolemn occaſions; was alſo choſen by them to be one of their morning week-dayes Preachers in the <hi>Abbey</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> Beſides,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Martins</hi> in the fields.</note> his conſtant Sabbath-dayes pains in another great Congregation, where he was a bleſſing to thouſands.</p>
               <p>Thence he was Ordered to be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Emanuel Colledge</hi> in this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, which not being a ſphere large enough for his activity, he was from thence removed to the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Trinity Colledge.</hi> Where what great good he did, they there can beſt tell; and that happy change proclaime's, from that confuſion (by reaſon of thoſe diſtracted times) in which he found it, to that orderly compoſure and frame, in which, through Gods bleſſing, he left it.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170050:28"/> How ſolicitous he was for their beſt welfare, his very frequent Preaching in their Chappel to them all, and his writing to their Seniors, ſpeak out fully. And we with them can truly bear witneſſe, how humble and loving to them he was in his carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, how ſtudious to keep up <hi>Colledg</hi>-Exerciſes, how zealous to advance Piety and Learning; and for that purpoſe to countenance and prefer ſuch as he obſerved to be eminent in either. Long ſo may that famous <hi>Society</hi> flouriſh, and long may ſuch be continued with them, who ſhall induſtriouſly endevour to carry on his happy beginnings to perfection.</p>
               <p>As he was an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity man,</hi> he was zealouſly careful of</p>
               <p>It's <hi>honour,</hi> (which the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe can witneſſe) in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindely conteſt about it: and alſo his care in collecting the decayed <hi>Antiquities</hi> of it, whoſe pains in that Argument, I deſire may not die with him.</p>
               <p>Of its <hi>priviledges,</hi> as always, ſo eſpecially the two years together, in which he was <hi>Vice-Chancellour,</hi> for which he ſuffered in ſome mens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes unjuſtly.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170050:28"/>
               <p>Of its <hi>profit and emolument,</hi> being<note place="margin">By Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bancrofts</hi> will. Sir <hi>John Wollaſton</hi> Alderman of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> a ſpecial means of procuring to it from the Parliament, the <hi>Lambeth Library,</hi> which of right fell to us: and from a noble Knight, both a yearly ſtipend for a <hi>Mathematick</hi> Lecturer, and alſo large ſummes of money for the fitting of the publick Library, that it might be of publick uſe, which others doe not more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, then he endevoured; for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment whereof the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is more wayes then one his deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
               <p>Finally, of the <hi>general good, and well-ordering of it:</hi> ſurely it was his careful thought in private with himſelf; for I am ſure it was the matter of his private diſcourſe with others. Scarce was there a time that he met with us, but he was asking or propoſing ſomething or other that way. It ſeemeth his care was to keep up thoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would ruine: which made <hi>Grotius</hi> pronounce many <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De jure belli ac pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis lib. 3. ca. 11. ſect. 10.</note> to be worſe then the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> for they 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 5. would let the company of Prophets alone, even where they kept Garriſon: it hath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170050:29"/> been not from the good will of theſe men, but from the favour of God, and our Governours, that in the midſt of warres wee have enjoyed the like ſafety and protection. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſeeing as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of old<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronym. Mercurialis de arte gymnaſtica. Ariſtotles de anima lib. cap.</hi> Jer. 29. 7.</note> were wont to diſpute in the Temple of <hi>Peace,</hi> till it was demoliſhed, and <hi>Intellectus</hi> being in <hi>quiete,</hi> ſuch a Temple is a <hi>Students</hi> beſt ſanctuary. Pray we for the Peace of the <hi>State, for in it we ſhall have peace,</hi> and not be given up to the fury of thoſe whoſe little Learning ſerveth them onely to declame againſt what they want: near of kin to the <hi>Fox</hi> in the <hi>Fable,</hi> or to them whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ardaliones, Burning or bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 21. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>men, and skilful onely to deſtroy.</hi> But to return to our Brother. This he was as an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As a <hi>Divine,</hi> he was ſound in the<note place="margin">Tit. 1. 13.</note> Faith, Orthodox in his Judgement, firmly adhering to the good old do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> that which in this our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Whitaker, Perkins, Davenant, Ward,</hi> and others maintained in their times: and in the other Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170050:29"/> among other great <hi>Names</hi> there, hee was a very great Admirer of the right Reverend and Judicious Dr. <hi>Robert Abbot,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and I wiſh hee had there many more ſuch Admirers. The Doctrines of <hi>Gods Soveraignty in his decrees, of his inconditionate moſt free electing love, of his free grace againſt free will, and the power of nature in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals; of juſtification by the imputed righteouſneſse of Chriſt, againſt the perfection o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> inherent righteouſneſs now attainable by us in this life; of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in grace againſt the Apoſtacy of the Saints, and the like.</hi> Were not with this our Brother, (as they are now called by ſome) <hi>Sects and Notions, matters onely of</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Steven Gardners</hi> dialect, who calls juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Learning-Fox</hi> Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. <hi>Tom. 2. pa.</hi> 726.</note> 
                  <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and curioſity, and of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian faction.</hi> But of the life-blood of Faith, which at his death, (as he expreſſed to his friend) he had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular comfort from; and in his life firmly believed, conſtantly Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by his Pen endevoured to maintain and defend, and that againſt the great daring Champion of the contrary errors, whom the abuſive wits in this Univerſity with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170050:30"/> boldneſſe could ſay, none here durſt adventure upon, whoſe immodeſt ſcurrility his Learned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that daring adverſary (which he had made ſo fair a progreſſe in) had ſhordy confuted, had not he by his more ſudden death been therein prevented. This of him as a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</p>
               <p>As a Miniſter of the Goſpel; In his Preaching he was plain, powerful, ſpiritual, frequent, and laborious; for beſides, what in that kinde he did, as to the Univerſity in this place, and in the Colledge Chappel, which was very happy in his often pains there.</p>
               <p>In the Town he ſet up one Lecture<note place="margin">St. <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els.</hi>
                  </note> every Sabbath morning in one Church, performed only by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and chearfully frequented by a great confluence of both <hi>Scholars</hi> and Townſmen. And another in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother<note place="margin">All-Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</note> Church every Lords day in the afternoon, in which he bare at leaſt, the fourth part of the burden, and both <hi>gratis,</hi> as there are many more ſuch Lectures here performed, much about the ſame rate, weekly by other pious learned men, and more
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170050:30"/> (I believe) then are in any <hi>Town</hi> or <hi>City</hi> upon thoſe terms in all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In <hi>Cambridge</hi> now, more then any where I know, or in theſe latter times have heard of, you may have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the more to<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 18.</note> the honour (I ſay not of ſuch thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hearers, but) of God in the firſt place, and then of that <hi>Reformation</hi> which ſo many do ſo traduce and ſpit at: as alſo of thoſe more noble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Preachers, who ſo freely offer to God that which coſteth them ſo much, for which of men they receive nothing.</p>
               <p>But this place did not bound the courſe of this our laborious Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers Miniſtry; but as it is ſaid of<note place="margin">Matth. 9. 35.</note> our <hi>Saviour <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that he went about all Cities and Villages tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and preaching,</hi> and of <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 19. <hi>Vulg.</hi>
                  </note> that from <hi>Hieruſalem, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, per circuitum,</hi> round about, and that to <hi>Illyricum,</hi> which was in a right line 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>German</hi> miles, (as <hi>Pareus</hi> upon the place computes it) he did <hi>fully preach the Goſpel,</hi> imitating herein, (as <hi>Hierome</hi> obſerves,) his Lord and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>in</hi> Amos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Maſter, that <hi>Sun of righteouſneſse,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170050:31"/> whoſe <hi>going forth is from the ends of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the Heaven, and his circuit unto the ends of it: ut ante eum terra defice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, quam praedicandi ſtudium.</hi> In theſe their bleſſed ſteps, this our <hi>Brother</hi> trod and followed them in his painful Miniſtery, diligently Preaching (when he had occaſion to be abroad) in remoter parts; but eſpecially in many Towns and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges nearer hand, round about the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity,</hi> being a means to ſet up <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures</hi> in many of them, and very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aſſiſting in them: and as our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> is obſerved, by ſome <hi>Divines</hi> to have Preached more frequently, the nearer he was to his departure: ſo this his faithful Servant, as it were preſaging that his day would be but ſhort, towards his evening made the more haſte and ſpeed in his journey, towards his end, yet more <hi>abounded</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>in this work of the Lord, and now findes that his labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> This of him as a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, as he was a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>-</p>
               <p>He was active for God, as his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>going up and down, and doing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10. 38</note> 
                  <hi>good.</hi> And although otherwiſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170050:31"/> yet when the caſe required it, bold in a good cauſe.</p>
               <p>Spiritual in communion, ſo that now he is <hi>dead,</hi> I fear we ſhall want ſuch a <hi>quickner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fruitful in diſcourſe, by which we might diſcover the frame of his<note place="margin">Loquere, ut te videam.</note> ſpirit; frequent in asking queſtions, which was both his <hi>humility,</hi> and Chriſtian good <hi>Hushandry,</hi> thereby to improve himſelf, and time, and company.</p>
               <p>Affable to others, of much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in low thoughts of himſelf, and of great integrity and ſingleneſs of heart, towards God, his truth, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, wayes, and ſervants.</p>
               <p>Of a very publick ſpirit, and much affected with the various conditions of the <hi>State,</hi> eſpecially of the <hi>Church</hi> and people of God.</p>
               <p>A moſt loving Husband to his Wife, and dutiful Sonne to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               <p>And in his life time much helpful to his other relations, many poor, both of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and <hi>Town,</hi> will now feel the want of his bounty, which they taſted of in his life, and both they and others had done more
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170050:32"/> at his death, (as appeareth by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of it in the draught of his Will) had not the ſuddenneſſe of it prevented it.</p>
               <p>In a long continued <hi>Quartan,</hi> God had knocked at his door, which in the <hi>interim</hi> of his recovery awakened him to get all within ready againſt his now coming in, which though to us unexpected, yet found not him unprepared.</p>
               <p>In his ſhort ſickneſſe, to one of his friends he expreſſed (as I before hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) his great comfort and joy in Gods free diſcriminating electing love, which therefore I would have none among us diſpute a way againſt the time that their turn cometh; to my ſelf, about half an hower before his departure (which I hoped had been much farther off) when I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him about the ſetling of his outward eſtate, and inward peace, hee readily and without the leaſt heſitancy anſwered me, <hi>through the mercy of God in Chriſt it was made, and that he quietly reſted in it.</hi> It ſeemeth that (as it was ſaid of one) he had <hi>his faith at his fingers ends,</hi> and having before <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170050:32"/> all diligence to make his calling and election ſure,</hi> though ſomewhat ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly called out of this life, he had <hi>an abundant entrance</hi> now ſet open to him <hi>into the everlaſting Kingdome</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus from this Univerſity (as the <hi>Jewes</hi> uſe to ſay of a Learned man when he dieth) <hi>requiſitus eſt in Academiam coeleſtem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to himſelf, having lived a <hi>fruitful</hi> and gracious life, as <hi>Clemens</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prima ad Corinth. pag. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>Romanus</hi> ſpeaks of ſome of the firſt and beſt Biſhops, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee cloſed up all with an happy and bleſſed death.</p>
               <p>As to others, he lived approved, and died deſired; and by my ſelf (I am ſure) and by very many, by moſt that ever rightly knew him (I believe) very much lamented. So that although wee leave <hi>Ennius</hi> to his <hi>Nemo me Lachrymis,</hi> &amp;c. yet this our Brother with <hi>Solon</hi> (if his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility would have ſuffered him) might have ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I have heard, that at Dr. <hi>Whitakers</hi> Funerals, in this place there were very many wet eyes, and I believe now at Dr. <hi>Hills</hi> are very
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170050:33"/> many ſad hearts; but why ſhould we grudge him his happineſſe? who may ſay to us, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> did to the <hi>Jewes, Weep not for me, but weep</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 23. 28</note> 
                  <hi>for your ſelves,</hi> and for the many ſad evils, which hee is taken from, you may be left to ſee and feel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 1. anſwerable to which the <hi>Jewes</hi> have<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a ſaying of ſuch good mens deaths, <hi>Quando luminaria patiuntur Eclypſin ſignum malum eſt mundo,</hi> It is an ill ſign to the world, when the <hi>Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of Heaven</hi> are Eclypſed. <hi>Deus avertat omen:</hi> But certain it is, that wee have loſt in him a great good help to keep off ſuch judgements, and that at ſuch a time, in which he could bee ill ſpared. But wee moſt humbly ſubmit to the Soveraign will of that Supreme All-ſufficient God, who <hi>can of ſtones raiſe up children</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>unto Abraham,</hi> and who, (whatever we doe) ſtandeth not in need of his beſt fitted ſervants for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his work. Onely the fewer and weaker our hands are which are left, the more wee have need to beſtirre them for his truth, and in his ſervice: or rather, the more earneſtly ſpread and lift them
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170050:33"/> up to him, that he would carry on his own work by his own ſtrength; and if it be his will, (as the <hi>Jewes</hi> from that in <hi>Eccleſ. 1. 5. of the Suns</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antequam occidere ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Deus ſolem juſti alicujus, oriri facit ſolem juſti alterius. <hi>2 Kings 2. 13.</hi> Serm. 87.</note> 
                  <hi>riſing, and the Suns going down,</hi> are wont to ſay, that the ſame day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one great man dieth, another is raiſed up, a <hi>Joſhua</hi> to ſucceed <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Eli</hi>) that the mantle of this our <hi>Elijah</hi> may fall upon ſome <hi>Eliſha,</hi> that ſome may ariſe in his ſpirit and power, and that doubled, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith of <hi>Elijah, plus gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae dimiſit in terris quam ſecum porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit in coelos;</hi> ſo that the place of this our <hi>David</hi> may not bee left empty,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 25. In Dr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſmiths</hi> ſucceeding him in <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> but what is already happily ſupplied to the <hi>Colledge,</hi> may alſo be made up to the whole <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>Mean while, let not <hi>us</hi> or his ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neareſt <hi>Relations</hi> ſorrow as men without hope:</p>
               <p>Either of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> as though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he</hi> hath left us, God ſhould have left us alſo; but by his death let us take occaſion to love the <hi>world</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Robinſons.</hi> Eſſaies, <hi>cap.</hi> 62.</note> leſſe, out of which he is taken, and <hi>heaven</hi> more, whither he is gone before us, and where once wee ſhall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170050:34"/> for ever enjoy him, and bee there<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23.</note> with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially, becauſe there is no cauſe at all to weep as without hope of <hi>him,</hi> who undoubtedly reſteth in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and though dead, liveth and triumpheth in Heaven, where in that bleſſed <hi>Conſort</hi> hee now ſing's this joyful <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Text, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory? Now thanks be to God, who hath given us the victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170050:34"/>
               <head>SERMON II.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>1 COR. 15. 55.</bibl>
                  <q>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Text preſented <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> to us as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, in a double, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry different poſture.</p>
               <p>1. As armed, and ſo formidable: <hi>Death</hi> with its <hi>ſting,</hi> and the <hi>Grave</hi> with the <hi>victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. But ſecondly, (and which is principally intended) diſarmed, and ſo made contemptible: and here <hi>Death</hi> hath loſt its <hi>ſting,</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> the <hi>victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former we have lately conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered upon a more ſad occaſion, when we took view of the dark ſide of the cloudy pillar, and whiles the<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 30. Luke 9. 14.</note> true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> looketh on it onely, he may, with the <hi>Diſciples begin to fear,</hi> as he entreth into that cloud. But
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170050:35"/> now the bright ſide is turned to us, and the true <hi>Diſciple of Chriſt</hi> may hear out of this cloud that ſweet voice, <hi>This is my beloved Son.</hi> After<note place="margin">Luk. 9. 35.</note> a dark night, the day now breake's, and the <hi>ſhadowes,</hi> (even the ſhadow<note place="margin">Cant. 2. 17.</note> of death) fly away. The laſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is deſtroyed, and the true <hi>Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> who had fought under Chriſts banner, after the conflict ended, and the victory obtained, is now gotten into the <hi>valley of Berachah,</hi> there in<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20. 26.</note> God, to triumph over theſe his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. With this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting! O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> And ſo the point which remaineth to be treated on is, That</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>As to a true Believer, in and by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, death hath loſt its ſting, and the grave which ſwalloweth up all, ſhall at laſt it ſelf be ſwallowed up in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie:</hi> For ſo our Apoſtle here <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In locum.</note> flouriſh the words; as a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious triumphant Conquerour treading on the necks of theſe van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed enemies, cries <hi>victoria,</hi> and ſhout's out with triumphant ſong, <hi>O
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170050:35"/> death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words, as to the ſtrength and elegancy of the expreſſion, take notice of</p>
               <p>1. His Rhetorical <hi>Proſopopaeia</hi> and <hi>Apoſtrophe,</hi> in this <hi>Catacleuaſticall compellation, O death—O grave.</hi> It ſeem's this man of God durſt look theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, bugbears in the face, and ſpeak out to their heads without fear and aſtoniſhment.</p>
               <p>2. His as elegant, but ſtinging <hi>Interrogation. Where is thy ſting? Where is thy victory?</hi> Which addeth weight to the expreſſion, but yet more elevateth and ſleighteth the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as wholly vanquiſhed, and his power and terrour quite vaniſhed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> locum.</note> ſought for it cannot be found. This queſtion of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> being like that of <hi>Zebul</hi> to <hi>Gaal, Jndg. 9. 38. Where is now thy mouth?</hi> when hee ſtood before him ſpeechleſſe. Or rather like that <hi>chap.</hi> 1. of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Where is the wiſe man? where is the Scribe?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 20. which he had anſwered before, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. in his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they were deſtroyed and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170050:36"/> brought to nought. And ſo here, when he asketh the queſtion, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> he alſo had before anſwered it, in his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ver. 26. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ver. 54. both words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrongly ſignificant to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is deſtroyed, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, made <hi>idle</hi> and vain, that it can do nothing, at leaſt to our hurt, whileſt its ſting is broken, and quite taken out, the <hi>Bee</hi> is become a <hi>Drone.</hi> It is as a <hi>vipera medicata,</hi> that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good it may doe, to be ſure it can doe us no harm, but rather as <hi>Moſes</hi> his Serpent, becometh a ſtaff in his hand to ſupport him; which before he was afraid of, and ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from, and might he not then well ask the queſtion, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then adde, <hi>O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> when he had immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before in the fore-going verſe ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it ſelf was <hi>ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>ſtrong man is overcome by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 11. 21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſtronger,</hi> who by taking out this ſting, <hi>hath taken from him his armor:</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170050:36"/> and ſo even <hi>the lawful captive of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 49. 24. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>mighty is taken away,</hi> and <hi>the prey of the terrible delivered,</hi> whileſt this terrible enemy is thus deſpoiled, and this painted Lion is not <hi>armed,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is now a foul fault in Deaths <hi>Heraldry:</hi> Now as an <hi>Ex-Conſul,</hi> a <hi>quondam Tyrant,</hi> like the <hi>beaſt that was, and is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>not,</hi> and <hi>miſerum eſt fuiſſe,</hi> our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies miſery, but our happineſſe; when, being once landed on the ſhore of Eternity, we ſhall with everlaſting joy, look on death, and the grave, with all their power and terrour, as at <hi>waters that are paſt;</hi> and amongſt<note place="margin">Job. 11. 16.</note> the many other dead corpſes of our Egyptian enemies, ſee <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 30. with 15. 1. Revel. 15. 2, 3.</note> alſo <hi>dead on the ſea-ſhore;</hi> and then <hi>having the harps of God, ſing the ſong of</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Lamb:</hi> Or if you will this of the Apoſtle in the Text, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> In which<note place="margin">Myrothec. pag. 37, 31.</note> words <hi>Came<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> think's the Apoſtle hath ſpecial reſpect to that great promiſe of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Matth. 16. 18. that <hi>the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt his Church;</hi> which <hi>gates of Hell,</hi> he expound's of the power of <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>grave,</hi> which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170050:37"/> being weakned and annull'd by the death of Chriſt, he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhall not be able <hi>altogether to prevail,</hi> as that compound <hi>Verb</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth. Something indeed <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> are able to doe, and that to the elect of God; thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe <hi>cords</hi> and <hi>chains of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>death,</hi> will be able to draw them to the <hi>grave,</hi> and there for a time keep them bound under their dominion, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>valebit, ſed non praevalebit,</hi> as he ſpeaketh of death; but at worſt this will not be alwaies, time will be when this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Text, which have ſo long kept us priſoners in the grave, ſhall at laſt themſelves, as condemned priſoners, <hi>be caſt into the lake of fire,</hi> Rev. 20. 14. when the the <hi>Elect,</hi> after all their fore-taſtes of this mercy here, as it were by faith, antedating this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and before-hand tuning the Inſtrument againſt that bleſſed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort,</hi> being then fully and for ever freed from this <hi>laſt enemy,</hi> as well as all others, ſhall ſing out aloud this bleſſed triumphant ſong, which ſhall then fill Heaven and Earth with the ſound of it; <hi>O death, where is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170050:37"/> thy ſting? O grave, where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But more particularly, That <hi>death</hi> even in this life, hath loſt its <hi>ſting</hi> to ſuch, appeareth from this, that 1. for any hurt it can doe them, they have been enabled to ſleight and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it. 2. In regard of that great good it bring's with it, they have earneſtly deſired that it would come, and as chearfully welcomed it, when it did.</p>
               <p>1. For <hi>any hurt it can doe them, they have been able to ſleight and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it,</hi> and (as it is here in the Text) to triumph over it, <hi>O death, where is your ſting?</hi> As though he had ſaid to this Serpent, you make an hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but you hurt not. Your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non makes a roaring, but its no bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let that you ſhoot but powder, which cannot blow me from Chriſt, and my ſtedfaſtneſſe, ſuch <hi>Shaw-fowls</hi> doe not ſcare me, which inſtead of being affrighted, I can ſmile at. <hi>Mors Chriſtianis ludus eſt.</hi> So <hi>Vincentius,</hi> nay, (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expreſſeth it)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> 1 Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is ſuch as tendereſt Virgins, and weakeſt children could laugh at; and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170050:38"/> although they were more ſerious then with Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> to die<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bacon Aug. ment. l. 4. ca. 1. p.</hi> 205 So alſo <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatian</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a jeſt, and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement. <hi>Ecce miſer tuam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aſſaſti, verte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teram.</hi>
                  </note> with a light jeſt in their mouths, yet they could with an holy deriſion of their cruelleſt Tormentors, as <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius,</hi> when now broiling on the grid-iron to <hi>Decius,</hi> in that facetious <hi>Sarcaſme. Behold, wretched Tyrant, thou haſt roaſted thine own part, turn the other.</hi> It would be too long to relate in particular how ambitious, and ſometimes too forward <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Chriſtians have been by crowds to preſſe to death and martyrdome, blunting the edge of the keeneſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors ſwords, and choaking thoſe ravenous beaſts of prey, whoſe <hi>throats were as open ſepulchres;</hi> or,<note place="margin">Rom. 3. 13.</note> like the <hi>Behemoth, Job</hi> 40. 23. think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſwallow down all, the <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> age being enabled chearfully to endure the greateſt <hi>hardſhip,</hi> and the <hi>weakeſt</hi> ſex to over-maſter <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> pains and torments, as ſo many flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, or medicinable blood-lettings. So <hi>Anne Ayſcough</hi> in that caſe could ſubſcribe her ſelf, <hi>Such an one as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts and Monum. <hi>Tom. 2. pa.</hi> 776.</note> 
                  <hi>neither wiſhed death, nor feared his might, and as merry as one that was bound for Heaven.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170050:38"/> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon theſe words ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> in the Text, and the ſame may we of <hi>Hers</hi> and many others. <hi>Noble ſouls!</hi> that could deſpiſe that, which others trembled at, like <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and by his mighty conduct, <hi>leading captivity captive,</hi> triumphing<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 8</note> over death, the fear whereof keep's others in bondage. Such a miracle<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 15. <hi>Serm. 26. in Cantic.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, he ſaw in dying <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rardus, hominem in morte exultantem, &amp; inſultantem morti, exulting</hi> in death, and <hi>inſulting</hi> over it; a miracle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in regard of the greatneſſe of the thing, but none in reſpect of the ordinarineſſe of it, in many <hi>new,</hi> in more in former times of perſecution; but eminently in our Apoſtle, who might well ask death, where its ſting was? when in the firſt place for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hurt it could do him, could thus deſpiſe it, and triumph over it.</p>
               <p>2. But ſecondly, in regard of the<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Phil. 1. 21.</note> great gain he ſhould have by it, could earneſtly deſire that it would haſten to come, and as chearfully and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully welcome it, when it did.<note place="margin">Mors omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, multis remedium, probis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> votum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>1. A believer can heartily and earneſtly deſire it, <hi>cui vita in taedio,</hi> or rather <hi>in patientia, mors in deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170050:39"/> is weary of life, or patiently content to live, but willing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to die.</p>
               <p>And this not out of extremity of preſent anguiſh and pain, or heat of paſſion, as <hi>Elijah, Job, Jonah,</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Kin. 19. 4 Job 7. 15, 16. Jonah 4. 3</note> others, who upon that account <hi>long for death,</hi> and <hi>dig for it more then for hid treaſures,</hi> Job 3. 21.</p>
               <p>But in cool blood, upon moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious debate, <hi>Paul</hi> is in a <hi>ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two,</hi> and when he hath diſputed the caſe <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> he concludeth for a concluſion of this life, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be diſſolved or to be <hi>looſed,</hi> as ſome read that word, or rather <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Genev.</note> as <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> or, as our laſt Tranſlators render it to <hi>depart,</hi> as a travellour to return home, and there to be looſed from this worlds intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glements, as Charet or Coach-hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes uſe to be from their harneſs, when they come to the end of their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; for ſo the words both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>dimiſſio mors. Shindler</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifie; and ſo old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> in the ſame caſe maketh uſe of a like word, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 29. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> praying for a diſmiſſion, as a <hi>priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> from his chains, and a ſtranger to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170050:39"/> his home, where as a weary <hi>travellor,</hi> he may lie down and take his reſt: for ſo death, to ſuch, is frequently in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and other Authors expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>ſleep,</hi> and the burying place is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>ſleeping place,</hi> and both the <hi>grave</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 2. 2 Sam. 3. 31.</note> that carrieth to it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> both words ſignifying a <hi>bed</hi> to reſt and ſleep on; which they could not well have done, if death had retained its ſting, and ſo their graves had been as ſo many Vaults full of Scorpions, and themſelves like the <hi>Leviathan</hi> that hath ſharp-pointed ſtones ſpread under him, <hi>Job</hi> 41. 30. If ſo, it had been no <hi>molliter oſſa cubant,</hi> would have proved but a very uneaſie bed, not ſo to be deſired quietly to take our reſt in; this ſting therefore muſt of neceſſity be gone, ſeeing ſo many in their right wits have ſo heartily and earneſtly deſired that it might come.</p>
               <p>And what then? when it did<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eurip. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt.</hi>
                  </note> come, were they then as much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and affrighted at it, as the old man in the Fable, who weary of his burden, wiſhed for death; but when it came at his call, all in a fright, got
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170050:40"/> up with his load, and trudge away as faſt as his feet, or rather his fear could carry him? No, but</p>
               <p>2. Did not more earneſtly before defire it, then at its approach moſt gladly welcome it.</p>
               <p>Nor this neither with them, <hi>Job</hi> 3. 22. and ſome others, who by reaſon of extremity of outward or inward anguiſh, and wearineſſe of life, (as <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid, <hi>anguiſh is come upon me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe my life is yet whole in me:</hi> doe therefore exceedingly <hi>rejoyce, when they can finde the grave;</hi> which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them then too late finde they have little cauſe for, when, to their ſmart they will meet with infinite more miſery after death, then they did before. But they that have a <hi>lively</hi> faith in Chriſt, and in a <hi>dying</hi> hour can then act it, even when in a manner they lie ſpeechleſſe, (from conſideration of that greater good they then partly meet with, and are more fully then entring upon) can <hi>ſay,</hi> that the <hi>day of their death, is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>better then the day of their birth;</hi> ſo that whereas they cryed in that, they rejoice in this. And (as the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> did the day of their <hi>Martyrdom</hi>)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170050:40"/> account it their <hi>Natalitia,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly<note place="margin">Mar. 6. 21. Gen. 40. 20.</note> (as the manner was) moſt joyfully welcome and celebrate it. If it came in a natural courſe peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, nay, were it never ſo violent, yet receive the cruelleſt ſentence of it, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> did, with a <hi>Deo gratias.</hi> So they ſtory of S. <hi>Andrew,</hi> ſaluting the Croſſe on which he was to bee crucified, and ſaying, <hi>Take me from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Accipe me ab homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtro meo.</note> 
                  <hi>men, and reſtore me to my Maſter;</hi> as of <hi>Laurence Saunders,</hi> who when come to the ſtake at which he was to be burnt, kiſſed it, ſaying, <hi>Welcome the Croſse of Chriſt, welcome everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life:</hi> That whereas the <hi>meſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of death,</hi> to moſt men, is in it ſelf, and is ſo deſcrib'd in Scripture, very terrible, yet to a dying Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then acting a lively faith, is nothing ſo, but is entertained by him as a welcome meſſenger ſent from the Father, as to a childe at nurſe, to<note place="margin">Robinſon.</note> bring it home, where it ſhall be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided for, whileſt it tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth him from all his ſins and ſorrowes into that place and eſtate of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Browns</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into vulgar er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, <hi>li. 3. cap.</hi>
                  </note> bliſſe, where he ſhall never ſinne nor grieve more. <hi>Solinus</hi> his relation of the <hi>Swan's</hi> ſinging a little before her
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170050:41"/> death, is now accounted but a Fable; yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in one <note n="*" place="margin">De hiſtor. Animal. li. 9. cap. 12.</note> place confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and in another rendereth this reaſon of it, that then generous blood goeth to the heart, making it chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and that thence commeth the melody. I ſhall not undertake to aſſert either the relation, or the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it; but thus far may apply it, and ſay, that God promiſeth to his <hi>meek</hi> ſervants, that <hi>their hearts ſhall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 22. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>live for ever;</hi> and if for ever, then in death it ſelf; and thence it is that ſuch generous blood indeed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth then to ſuch hearts, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth many to end their lives, not in mournfull <hi>Elegies,</hi> but in moſt joyfull ſongs of praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, or without any dolorous ſenſe, or mournful complaint of the ſting of death: and where is it then, when it is thus <hi>earneſtly deſired,</hi> and ſo welcomly entertained?</p>
               <p>I grant that this is not ſo with all believers; <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in this caſe, did not ſing like the <hi>Swan</hi> but chatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 14.</note> as the <hi>Crane,</hi> and mourned as the <hi>Dove.</hi> And many may bee the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why God in wiſdome and faithfulneſſe may let ſome <hi>Believers</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170050:41"/> ſetting Sun, (at leaſt for a time) be muffled up in a cloud; &amp; the fault is in themſelves, that wheras Satan uſeth then moſt fiercely to caſt his <hi>fiery darts,</hi> they then are not carefull<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 10.</note> to hold up the <hi>ſhield of faith,</hi> which <hi>might quench them;</hi> but by their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or wilfull unbelief, take a courſe to thruſt them in deeper. The Bee<note place="margin">Animaſque in Vulnere ponunt. Virg. Geor. 4.</note> dieth when ſhe hath left her ſting in the wound; but if the man who is ſtung, careleſly let it alone, he may come to more ſmart by it, which, by his care timely to get it out, might be prevented; like careleſneſſe of a worſe ſting, breedeth greater ſmart in the caſe wee now ſpeak of. What therefore hath bin ſaid of a <hi>Believers</hi> ſecurity and comfort in this kinde, is to be underſtood of him as <hi>ſuch, viz.</hi> as he approveth himſelf to be a <hi>true believer,</hi> ſtirring up, and acting his faith in Chriſt. Otherwiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſecond death ſhal have no power over him, yet as he may be found careleſſe and negligent, the firſt death, if it ſurprize him in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, may very ſorely ſting and wound him: for as it is ſaid of <hi>mans laws,</hi> ſo it is as true of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170050:42"/> they favour not them that are aſleep, but ſuch as are awake and watchfull; and ſo to ſuch a <hi>wakefull</hi> Chriſtian, death is but a <hi>ſleep,</hi> indeed not it ſelf, not <hi>death</hi> but an enterance<note place="margin">Miſeri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideles mortem ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles vero quid niſi paſcham? Bernard. de natura &amp; dignit. divini a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris.</note> into life; as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>miſerable unbelievers call it death, but to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful believers, what is it but a paſſeover,</hi> but a Jubile? Though in it ſelf it be an enemy, yet by the death and life Chriſt, it is ſo diſarmed, that his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants can earneſtly deſire it, and gladly welcome it, by reaſon of the great good it bringeth with it; and as for all the evil it may ſeem to threaten or inflict, can ſecurely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it, and victoriouſly triumph over it, and with <hi>Paul</hi> here, ſay, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the further clearing whereof, that we more diſtinctly ſee in what ſenſe the ſting of death is taken out, and the power of the grave aboliſhed, as to believers, we are to take notice.</p>
               <p>1. Negatively, that is not ſo to be underſtood, as though they ſhould never either die, or meet with any anguiſh in death.</p>
               <p>1. That death ſhould not ſo far ſting them, as not to take away their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170050:42"/> bodily life from them, that was once given out of <hi>John</hi> ſhould be true of them, that they <hi>ſhould never die;</hi> for<note place="margin">John 21. 23.</note> ſo the longeſt lived of them have done, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. and the wiſeſt ſhall, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 49. 10. and the beſt oftentimes ſooneſt, as ſadly appeared in the untimely deaths of <hi>Judah's,</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh Joſiah:</hi> for as for this death, Gods ſentence, <hi>in dying, thou ſhalt die, or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> upon <hi>Adams</hi> ſin both to himſelf, and his whole po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity in ordinary courſe was, and continueth irreverſible; ſo that it is <hi>appointed for men</hi> (that is, <hi>generally</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>for all men) once to die,</hi> and becauſe the beſt are <hi>ſinfull</hi> whileſt they <hi>live,</hi> therefore <hi>they muſt die once,</hi> that <hi>once</hi> at laſt they may <hi>ſin no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> And if it be replyed, that that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> is taken off from the faithful, by Chriſt the <hi>ſecond Adam;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere, true; but yet in Gods moſt wiſe order and method, and that appeareth in two particulars.</p>
               <p>1. That although as to all curſe and wrath, and vindicative Juſtice, that was at firſt in it, all that is taken away by the imputation of Chriſts
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170050:43"/> ſatisfaction in our juſtification, yet the full freedom from it, yea, and from worſe evils then death is, (that we might be kept more humble, and dependant on God, and Heaven at laſt more welcome) is carried on and perfected by degrees. As on the one ſide, when the ſentence of death was paſſed upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo he was a dead man, yet he did not at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant preſently die; as deadly poiſon taken doth not alwaies kill preſently, but ſome after a ſhorter, and ſome after a longer time; ſo here on the other ſide, the moſt Soveraign medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine may not perfectly cure at the firſt, but when it hath had its perfect work; and although our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption by <hi>Chriſt</hi> be full, and our reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very by him will be made compleate, before he have done with us, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at the firſt we are (as I ſaid) in our juſtification, freed from the ſtate of death, yet the guilty malefactor is not alwaies preſently taken out of priſon upon his firſt receiving of his pardon, nor we at the firſt wholly quit from the miſeries of this life, nor from bodily death, no, nor from ſin, which to a godly heart is more
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170050:43"/> bitter then death. Did not our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father know, how both for the preſent and the future to improve them all to his own glory and our good, he could &amp; would cut <hi>ſhort his work in righteouſneſſe,</hi> and at the firſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 9. 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> at once pardon guilt, extinguiſh ſin, remove ſorrow, and aboliſh death, <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel omnia;</hi> but a man, (and ſo ſin and death in the godly) may have his deaths wound before he be quite dead, and a conquered captived enemy may for ſome time be kept alive, and have much good uſe made of him before he be finally executed; and ſo it is in this divine Oeconomy of Gods grace to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and in his proceſſe againſt theſe our enemies: he reſcueth us orderly, and by degrees, from one enemy after another, from one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of the ſame enemy after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>2. And (which is the ſecond par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in this divine method of God obſervable) <hi>he doth deliver us from the worſt firſt:</hi> firſt, from that which is wholly inconſiſtent with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to us, and our intereſt in him: as,</p>
               <p>Firſt, from his revenging wrath,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170050:44"/> and the condemning guilt of ſinne, and ſo from the ſtate of death, in our juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, 2. and 8. 1, 2, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And therewith from the dominion of ſin, in our ſanctification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 14.</p>
               <p>From the beeing and inexiſtence of ſin, at death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 23.</p>
               <p>And from death it ſelf, (which is left laſt, as leaſt hurtful) at the reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 26. 54. and it is abundantly enough for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that if not in this life, yet at death; or to be ſure at that laſt day, we ſhall have the full <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and perfect accompliſhment of this great work, when Chriſts reſcue of us ſhall be compleat, and death our laſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhall be wholly and for ever ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in victory. And this is the firſt <hi>Negative,</hi> Death hath not loſt its ſting, ſo as that <hi>believers ſhould</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver die.</p>
               <p>2. Nor ſo neither, that at their death they ſhould never feel any kind of ſmart and pain by the ſting of it.<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 3.</note> You heard that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> then wept ſore, and you read partly how poor, and partly what deſperate ſhifts, even
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170050:44"/> 
                  <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12. 12, 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. 2. 11. and <hi>David, 1 Sam.</hi> 21. 12, 13. and <hi>Peter, Matth.</hi> 26. 70. 72. 74. (three of the Scriptures greateſt worthies; the firſt famous for <hi>faith,</hi> the ſecond for <hi>valour,</hi> the third for <hi>boldneſſe in the cauſe of Chriſt</hi>) were driven to through fear of it; and ſad inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of latter times have ſhown that when many: ſecure obdurate ſinners have died (as you uſe to ſay) like <hi>lambs,</hi> ſome of the true <hi>ſheep</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> paſture have been then half worried by this <hi>evening wolf;</hi> in ſuch even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings theſe <hi>frogs of the inſernal pit</hi> oft croak aloud, and <hi>Belzebubs</hi> flies then ſwarm apace. Satan when now to be caſt out teareth moſt; in <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 2. 26. Exod. 14. 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Exodus,</hi> or out-gate from <hi>Egypt, Pharaoh</hi> purſueth with all his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, becauſe if then once gone, they will be out of his reach for ever; the <hi>Devil cometh down with greateſt wrath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 12. Deut. 25. 17. 18.</note> becauſe then <hi>he hath leaſt time;</hi> and when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is weak, <hi>Amalek</hi> muſt fall on the <hi>Rear,</hi> and do ſomething now or never. And hence it hath been, that poſſibly you may have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſome dying <hi>Saints</hi> groans to have been very deep, and ſeen their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170050:45"/> death-beds, (as <hi>Davids</hi> Couch) <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and ſwimming with tears.</hi> Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 6.</note> if</p>
               <p>Either guilt of ſin be then charged on the conſcience, as not pardoned.</p>
               <p>Or ſome defilement of ſinne then diſcovered and aggravated; if our faith then ſtumble, our hearts will ſink and fall, and be much bruiſed againſt the gates of death: a <hi>body of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 24</note> 
                  <hi>death</hi> will then lie very heavy on the weak ſick man, now haſting to his <hi>bodily death;</hi> and that ſin which ſo defile's him, that he cannot with freedome and ſerenity of ſpirit at other times appear before God in <hi>duty,</hi> will more abaſh him, when now he is to appear before him in <hi>death</hi> to receive his doom.</p>
               <p>And thus far (for the <hi>Negative</hi>) death hath not loſt its ſting, but partly doth, and partly may retain it, as to true believers.</p>
               <p>2. But (for the <hi>Affirmative</hi>) ſo, as that in this life, at death, and at the reſurrection, they may with <hi>Paul</hi> in the Text, ask where is it? For</p>
               <p>In the <hi>General,</hi> it is but this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward life that death can ſeiſe on; as our Saviour ſaid of other enemies, ſo
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170050:45"/> may we of this our laſt enemy, it <hi>can kill onely the body, and after that hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 12. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing more that it can doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> Or, if you ſay, that it was before granted, that it can, and ſometimes doth ſting their ſouls alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> All I anſwer is, that thanks be to God, yet it is not mortally, for on ſuch the <hi>ſecond death hath no power:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 6.</note> and then, if they eſcape that <hi>ſecond death,</hi> this <hi>firſt</hi> to them is but <hi>Larva mortis,</hi> (as he calls it) but a grim <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> of death, in the Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is reckoned for no death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for whoſoever <hi>believeth in me</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11. 26.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſhall not die for ever:</hi> ſo in the <hi>Original</hi> which our laſt <hi>Tranſlators,</hi> not unfitly (but as the <hi>Greek</hi> phraſe will bear) read it, <hi>ſhall never die,</hi> if not <hi>for ever,</hi> faith conſtrueth it <hi>never;</hi> though I die <hi>temporally,</hi> yet Scripture calleth it a <hi>ſleep,</hi> rather then <hi>death,</hi> if I doe not die <hi>eternally.</hi> This in the general.</p>
               <p>But more particularly this <hi>ſting of death</hi> is taken away from belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</p>
               <p>1. <hi>In this life, partly, in juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and partly in ſanctification;</hi> for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170050:46"/> the Apoſtle in the words following the Text, telleth us, that <hi>the ſting of death is ſin;</hi> and ſin ſting's us, both in its terrifying condemning guilt, binding over to puniſhment, and in its enſlaving power and pollution.</p>
               <p>1. Now the firſt wee are freed from in our <hi>juſtification,</hi> there is then <hi>peace, Rom.</hi> 5. 1. and no <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> Rom. 8. 1. <hi>we are paſſed from death unto life, 1 Iohn</hi> 3. 14. the deſtroying Angel <hi>paſſeth over</hi> and ſtrike's not, when the door-poſts and lintel are firſt <hi>ſtruck</hi> with the blood<note place="margin">Exod. 12. 12, 13. Luk. 2, 29, 30.</note> of the Paſchal Lamb. And how chearfully then doth old <hi>Simeon</hi> ſing his <hi>Nunc dimittis,</hi> when he hath got his Saviour in his arms, and <hi>his eyes have ſeen Gods ſalvation?</hi> There is no ſting of death that he complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, the kiſſes of Chriſts mouth have ſucked that out from a juſtified Believer; and then although the ſhadow of death ſhould ſit <hi>on my eye-lids,</hi> as they did on <hi>Iobs,</hi> yet if<note place="margin">Job 16. 16.</note> I can but then diſcover the <hi>eye-lids of the morning,</hi> but the firſt and leaſt<note place="margin">Job 41. 18.</note> out-lookings of Heaven upon my ſoul, in pardon and peace, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if broad day light, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170050:46"/> more glorious ſhine of <hi>the Sunne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>of righteouſneſſe;</hi> how painful ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever deaths ſting might otherwiſe have been, my <hi>Phoebus</hi> is my <hi>Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> ſo that there will be full <hi>healing under his wings;</hi> and <hi>O death, where is then thy ſting?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. And as for the defiling pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and enthralling power of ſinne, though it bee as painfull as the very guilt of it, is as a <hi>prick in the fleſh, ſting's deep, and prick's</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Cor. 12. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>the very heart, Acts</hi> 2. 37. yet a Believer in this life hath an heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plaiſter for this wound alſo, from the ſpirit of grace in his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification: and how quickly doth a clean wound heal? with how little pain doth a formerly well-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered body die? and with how much leſſe, doth a ſoul, not <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically purged,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritually ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,</hi> depart from this <hi>earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> which is ſo ſubject to be foul, and the very ſweeping raiſeth a duſt, our repentings not being without new defilings? Death is not dolorous when my death and my ſin do not meet, but ſo part, that when the one cometh, the other is
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170050:47"/> gone for ever; and how doth the undefiled Dove (which had before lien <hi>among the pots</hi>) then ſhine and gliſter, when now in her flight to Heaven, the <hi>Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhines on her wings, which are covered with ſilver, and her feathers with yellow gold?</hi> That I may allude to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 13, 14. with what joy and delight doth the now chaſte ſoul, when it hath given a bill of divorce to all her former <hi>Paramours, ruere in amplexus,</hi> now caſt her ſelf into the boſome and embraces of her beſt beloved? Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is no terrible ſight to ſee death, when the <hi>pure in heart</hi> (though now<note place="margin">Matth. 5. 1.</note> cloſing their eyes in the gloomy ſhadow of death) can even <hi>then ſee God,</hi> in the cleare glaſſe of a pure conſcience: there is no ſuch ſting in it to ſuch, to diſquiet them, but that without the help of other friends, they may cloſe their own eyes, and take their reſt in their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours</hi> arms, and their <hi>Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> boſome.</p>
               <p>Which leadeth me from the firſt part of the Believers freedome from the ſting of death, <hi>In this life,</hi> to the</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170050:47"/>
               <p>2. Second and greater, and that <hi>even in death it ſelf.</hi> So that when it<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Juſtin Martyr A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. 1.</hi>
                  </note> kills, it hurts, it ſtings not; but when they loſe their lives, death then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its ſting, and this many wayes: for whereas in the former poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhewed that to a worldly carnall man, one ſore prick of this ſting of death was, that it let out all that comfort which the life of his ſoul was wrapt up in. On the contrary here it will appear, that a Believer in the out-let of his life, hath his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as it is called, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 31.) his out-gate from all that which in this life moſt troubled and wounded him, when the <hi>world ſhall never trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> or <hi>the Devil tempt,</hi> nor <hi>God frown, nor we ſin any more for ever,</hi> then (I ſay) we are freed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>1. From all the troubles of this world, which, as to others, ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to the godly uſeth to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vexatious and troubleſome.</p>
               <p>A tempeſtuous ſea; and am I hurt if a tempeſt drive me out of it into harbor?</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Pſal. 84. 6. a valley of tears</hi> (ſo ſome read it) or <hi>of Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry trees</hi> (ſo others) the one are
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170050:48"/> moiſt, and others uſe to grow in more dry places, between them they may ſerve to make up a more complete <hi>Embleme</hi> of this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world, made up of <hi>woes and wants;</hi> and how often may you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-hear the ſad mourner complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Now wo is me that I ſojourn in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 120. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> lxx.</note> 
                  <hi>Meſhech?</hi> and that word ſignifieth how long he thinke's the time is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; and may you not ſee thoſe mourning <hi>Doves of the valleys</hi> mant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the wing, and ſaying, <hi>O that I indeed had wings like a Dove, that I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>might flee away, &amp; be at reſt.</hi> And that reſt death and the grave bring's us, for <hi>there the wicked ceaſe from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and there the weary be at reſt, Iob 3. 17. at reſt,</hi> from all ſickneſſes, pains, ſorrows, perſecutions, &amp;c. which here they either feel or fear, the one <hi>death</hi> end's and cure's, the other it prevent's.</p>
               <p>It put's an end to them, ſo that either they are not, their malice then ceaſeth, <hi>poſt fata quieſcit,</hi> or in caſe it prove <hi>immortal,</hi> ſo that their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty rageth againſt the dead bodies, eſtates, good name, and poſterity of Saints departed; yet the beſt is, they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170050:48"/> then feel it not. <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Fagius</hi> did not cry out from Heaven as hurt, when their bones (ſuppoſe the wiſe Inquiſitors miſtook not ſome others for theirs) were ridiculouſly burnt here in <hi>Cambridge</hi> divers years after their deaths, the dead man neither pine's nor ſtarve's, and though you ſtab him, he neither ſighe's nor groanes: the weary before, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others trouble themſelves with them then) are at reſt, and although men will not let them <hi>live in peace,</hi> yet in ſpite of their malice, with old <hi>Simeon,</hi> they <hi>depart in peace,</hi> what evil they before felt, is then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>And what they feared, is then prevented, they being taken away from the evil to come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 1. as uſually <hi>evil</hi> is then <hi>coming,</hi> when <hi>good</hi> men are <hi>going;</hi> and if ſo, it is then the Fathers love and care even haſtily to ſnatch away the child, when the wilde bull is broken looſe from the ſtake, and is now running upon him; as alſo the wiſe Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman haſteneth to get in his Corn, before the ſwine be put out into the field to root up all: the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170050:49"/> ordinary inſtances in this kinde, are, <hi>Joſiah,</hi> ſuddenly taken away, that his eyes might not ſee the evil that was to be brought upon his people, and ſo, though he died in war, yet he is ſaid to <hi>bee gathered to his grave in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>peace;</hi> and ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> is bid to <hi>go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and reſt, chap.</hi> 12. 13. before thoſe great claſhings and confuſions ſhould come, which had been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewn to him in the fore-going viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Book. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> dieth a little before <hi>Genſericus</hi> took <hi>Hippo,</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> before. <hi>Heidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> was loſt, to whom (if you pleaſe)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wilſon</hi> of the life of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>James.</hi>
                  </note> you may adde Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> for whom the <hi>Purſivant</hi> was ſent a day or two after he was buried. And is then the man hurt, who by this means is ſet out of harms way? Or, is our traveller to Heaven the worſe traveller, or in a worſe caſe, for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up his Inne betimes, before the ſtorm come, or he be benighted in a wilderneſſe? At death the world will never fight or fright us more, and where then is its ſting?</p>
               <p>2. Nor will then the Devil bee ever able to tempt us any more; his<note place="margin">Ephes. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> are <hi>fiery darts,</hi> but then (thanks be to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170050:49"/> God) we are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, out of gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 7.</note> his temptations are <hi>pricks in the fleſh,</hi> and there let them ſtick; but the happineſſe is, that in death wee have left our fleſh behinde us. This <hi>Pharaoh</hi> may then (as was before ſhewed) purſue us moſt fiercely with all his forces; but then it may confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently be ſpoken to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, <hi>Fear not, ſtand ſtill, and ſee the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſalvation of the Lord, which he will ſhew to you this day, for theſe Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans whom you have ſeen to day, ye ſhall ſee them again no more for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Devil who had the <hi>power of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diabolus per quod poteſtatem habuit, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eſt. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>death, Heb.</hi> 2. 14. hath by death his commiſſion and power abrogated and aboliſhed. For,</p>
               <p>The ſouls of departed Saints, are then out of his reach.</p>
               <p>And as for their dead bodies, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may be, and have been abuſed by wicked men, the Devils inſtruments, yet it hath been juſtly queſtioned, whether the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf immediately have any ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over them. We read once of his<note place="margin">Jude v. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> contending with <hi>Michael the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel,</hi> about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and if the thing he contended for, were
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170050:50"/> (as it is uſually conceived) to have the place where it was buried diſcovered. It is plain from <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. 6. that in that conflict he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and is there then any ſting in death, when after it the world ſhall never any more trouble, nor the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil tempt?</p>
               <p>3. Nor (which is a far greater word) God <hi>frown,</hi> which yet in the time of our life he ſeeth juſt cauſe ſometimes to doe, and to vail his face from us; but then we come to live, not by faith, which admits of doubting, but by<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 12. Rev. 22. 4.</note> viſion, and that <hi>face to face:</hi> that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will be (as 2 <hi>Sam. 23. 4.) without clouds,</hi> becauſe we ſhall be above them, and in neareſt conjunction with the<note place="margin">Jam. 1. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Father of Lights, with whom there is no over ſhadowing;</hi> whatever the loanſom eſtrangments be that we meet with here, yet when <hi>Lazarus</hi> is once dead, he who was kept out of the rich mans<note place="margin">Luke 16. 32.</note> gates, is then found in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the place of warmeſt love.</p>
               <p>And that moſt lively warmth, moſt lively felt, in this chill and dark eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of death, <hi>in it there is light, Zech.</hi> 14. 7. in <hi>grace</hi> as well as in <hi>nature,</hi> the <hi>afternoon Sun</hi> is oftentimes very warm,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170050:50"/> and the ſetting Sun ſhines out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times moſt gloriouſly. So <hi>Oecolampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> making good the ſplendor of his own name) now dying, and that of an uncomfortable death, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>plague,</hi> could lay his hand upon his breaſt, &amp; ſay, <hi>hic abundè lucis eſt: here, here</hi> in this dark evening is abundant light, <hi>then then</hi> in that gloomy ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death have humble Beleevers (and oftentimes none more then they who before had been moſt ſad and broken-hearted) met with divineſt raptures &amp; raviſhments of Gods love, with gloriouſeſt ſhines, and moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſmiles of his countenance, and ſweeteſt kiſſes of his mouth, as the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mother kiſſeth the ſweet babe, and ſo layeth it down to ſleep. So the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Maimonid. More. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voch. parte tertia cap. 51. ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Buxtorf. Lexic. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin. ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Idem in Florileg. Hebr. pag. 205.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Maſters expound that <hi>Deut.</hi> 34. 5. of <hi>Moſes</hi> his dying <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Jehovae,</hi> as though God did take away his ſoul with a kiſſe; and ſo of their 903 kindes of death which they uſe to reckon up, this their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the death which commeth by ſuch a kiſſe, they ſay is <hi>omnium placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſima,</hi> of all moſt pleaſant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: which, they ſay alſo, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> only dyed of;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170050:51"/> but many beſides them, through Gods mercy have at that time known what the kiſſes of Chriſts mouth mean. And yet this both in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aarons</hi> deaths is to this purpoſe ſingularly remarkable, that whereas you read of Gods bidding <hi>Moſes</hi> to goe up to<note place="margin">Deut. 32. 49. 50. Numb. 20. 25, 26. <hi>Heinſii ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit. ſacrae in</hi> Matth. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and there die, and of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron,</hi> to go up to mount <hi>Hor,</hi> and ſtrip him of his garments &amp; die there, you ſhall not finde in either places, that <hi>ut capiſtrati ad mortem mali trahebantur;</hi> that as Malefactours they were drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to it as to an execution; but on the contrary, without the leaſt relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctance, they did as they were bid, like (me thinks) well natured children, although others of the Family ſit up latter, and it may be have greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions preparing for them, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out crying, or the leaſt whimpering, make themſelves ready, and go up to bed when their Father bids them, and well they might, although others ſtaid behinde, and were to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with <hi>Canaans</hi> milk and hony, which they were cut ſhort of, ſeeing they were thus ſent to bed with a kiſſe, never to have the leaſt appearance of a frown more.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170050:51"/>
               <p>4. But might we here <hi>adde</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 28. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſin more,</hi> you may ſay, this <hi>would ſeal up the ſumme,</hi> complete all, and leave of this ſting neither mark nor remembrance. Nor will this be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore in the laſt place I ſhall be bold to add this too. For as ſin in <hi>this life,</hi> had (as to the Beleever) loſt its condemning guilt, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo in <hi>death,</hi> it will be deprived of its beeing, or inexiſtence; indeed as long we ſhal here continue to dwell in theſe <hi>houſes of clay,</hi> it will be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that which will keep po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſion, and have its dwelling in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 17. but when our ſouls ſhall then be diſlodged of our bodies, this incroaching and troubleſome <hi>Inmate</hi> ſhall once for ever be thruſt out of doors from both bodies and ſouls together; the <hi>death of our body</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering us perfectly from this <hi>body of death,</hi> by which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted whether be meant this our <hi>mortal body,</hi> or the <hi>body of ſin,</hi> which<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom. 7. 24.</hi> Docet non finiri hos conflictus quandiu mortale corpus circumgeſtamus, quando corpus peccati ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando exuemus, Paraeus in locum.</note> is more deadly. I grant the latter, but would not exclude the former, becauſe both of them are put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170050:52"/> as when <hi>Samſon</hi> died, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> died alſo together with<note place="margin">Judg. 16. 30. <hi>Vide Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. in V. T. incerti Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris. Canta brig. 1653. In</hi> Lev. 11. 25. See Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> on Eccleſ. 7. 1.</note> him. This (ſome think) was typed out by that in the <hi>Law,</hi> where it is ſo often ſpoken of mens <hi>being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean until the evening;</hi> but more fully and plainly aſſerted in the New Teſtament, where the ſouls of <hi>juſt men</hi> once got to Heaven, are ſaid to be <hi>made perfect, Heb.</hi> 12. 23. Other places are brought by ſome to the ſame purpoſe, as <hi>that Rom. 6. 7. He he that is dead is freed from ſin,</hi> which though meant of a death to ſin in mortification, yet alludes to what is in natural death, as Interpreters agree upon the place, and <hi>thoſe</hi> expreſſions of Chriſts preſenting us to himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>faultleſse, Jude 24. not having ſpot, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, Eph.</hi> 5. 27. which to our particular perſons is done in death, <hi>Ecleſ.</hi> 12. 7. and <hi>that</hi> alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 26. where death is ſaid to be the laſt enemy which is to be deſtroyed, which they conceive it could not be, if ſin ſhould remain in us undeſtroyed after death: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe places may ſeem to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a ſatisfying anſwer, I wave them, and content my ſelf with that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170050:52"/> one before mentioned. I Confeſſe ſome <note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>B.</hi> his <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae legis pag.</hi> 118.</note> 
                  <hi>Divines</hi> of very great worth, conceive it is not <hi>death,</hi> but <hi>Cinere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> that wholy rids us of ſin, <hi>i. e.</hi> that we are not wholy freed from it, as ſoon as the ſoul is departed, and the body is now dead, but when it is turned into duſt and aſhes: and this they would inferre from the inſtance of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who after he had been<note place="margin">John 11.</note> dead four dayes, was raiſed up to life, yet ſo as he <hi>died again,</hi> which yet he ſhould not have done, if the Image of God had in his firſt death been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in him, and ſo he wholly freed from ſin. To which I briefly anſwer</p>
               <p>1. That it is no good way to prove that to be the ordinary and general courſe which God takes with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe poſſibly it might be ſo in <hi>Lazarus</hi> his particular and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary inſtance, concerning whom buſily to enquire what kind of death his was, or in what ſtate his ſoul was, in that <hi>quatridium mortis,</hi> I thinke would be too preſumptuous curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity.</p>
               <p>2. Although the Image of God in him might not be made perfect upon his firſt dying, and therefore hee
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170050:53"/> might die again the ſecond time, whileſt ſome conſequents of ſin, (as mortality) yet clave to him, yet it will not thence follow, that ſin abode in him, no more then that a Saint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted lieth under the power of ſin, though he doe continue under the power of death, which is a conſequent of ſin, till the reſurrection. Not that I determine that <hi>Lazarus,</hi> after his firſt dying and riſing again, lived all his time after without ſin, in which to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine any thing either way, were raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but onely to deny the inference, that becauſe the Image of God was not every way completed upon his firſt death, ſo that he died again, therefore it was not reſtored in <hi>this,</hi> as to his being freed from ſin, which I conceived ſaints departed are, though till the laſt day they lie under the power of death, which yet was brought into the world by ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
               <p>3. For the ordinary courſe, as I beleeve the dead body is no proper ſubject for ſin, ſo I conceive all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> who deny a <hi>Popiſh Purgatory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13. Rev. 21. 27.</note> or <hi>middle ſtate after death,</hi> muſt needs confeſſe, that the ſoul before the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170050:53"/> body be turned to duſt and aſhes, is<note place="margin">Sicque ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium tela abrumpitur <hi>Paraeus.</hi>
                  </note> got to Heaven, into which no unclean thing entreth; and therefore as ſoon as it is looſed from the body, it is ſo looſed from ſin, that it may have a ready flight, and free entrance unto that undefiled Manſion.</p>
               <p>And therefore I cannot but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to him who calls Death <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſay with <hi>Ambroſe, quid eſt mors niſi peccatorum ſepultura?</hi> that however it be the curſe of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to die in their ſins, <hi>John</hi> 8. 21. 4. yet for the godly, death in them kills ſin, and is buried in their grave, and ſo ſin and death, which were before friends, in our death prove deadly enemies; <hi>peccatum peperit mortem &amp; filia devoravit matrem,</hi> ſin at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got and <hi>brought forth death,</hi> and death<note place="margin">Jam. 5. 17.</note> at laſt deſtroyed ſin as the worm kills the tree that bred it. <hi>Death came by ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 12. Mr. <hi>Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in</hi> his Sermon <hi>on</hi> Luk. 4. 18. <hi>pag.</hi> 66.</note> and ſin goeth out by death, and ſo ſin diſ-armeth it ſelf, taketh out its own ſting; and may we not then well ſay, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory? viz.</hi> when <hi>death</hi> it ſelf, is thus killed, as you uſe to ſay, <hi>quick-ſilver is killed,</hi> when ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as it is made medicinable.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170050:54"/>
               <p>And the <hi>grave,</hi> which ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up all, is it ſelf <hi>ſwallowed up in victory, Captivity led captive</hi> and this our enemy not only ſubdued that it cannot hurt us, but alſo made to ſerve under our victorious Conquerer, ſo as to deſtroy our worſt enemy, ſin I mean, which we had moſt cauſe to be afraid of, and which above all made death terrible.</p>
               <p>And thus we have ſeen how the ſting of death is taken out both in life and death from a Believer; but for all this all is not yet done, for all the time that we continue dead, death in ſome reſpect continueth his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whileſt the grave keepes our bodies priſoners, how hath it loſt the victory? There is therefore ſomething yet behind, and will that good God who hath thus far led us, here leave us? that as <hi>Rachel died, when now it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 35. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>was but a little way to come to Ephrath,</hi> ſo when one ſtroak more would bring us to ſhore, we ſhould ſink in the harbour? O no.</p>
               <p>As on the one ſide <hi>David</hi> from good experience could ſtyle God <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 2.</note> a God, <hi>who performeth,</hi> or <hi>finiſheth,</hi> or <hi>perfecteth all for me,</hi> and <hi>whom he loveth,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170050:54"/> he loveth to the end, John</hi> 13. 1.</p>
               <p>So on the other ſide, as for his and their enemies, <hi>when he beginneth, he will make an end, 1 Sam.</hi> 3. 12. nor will he with <hi>Joaſh,</hi> when he hath<note place="margin">2 Kings 13 18, 19.</note> ſmitten twice or thrice, for want of giving the laſt ſtroak fall ſhort of compleating the victory.</p>
               <p>3. And that will be at the laſt day of the generall Reſurrection, till which time, death as it were <hi>lived,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 14</note> 
                  <hi>reigned,</hi> and kept the field, and the grave continued his victory; but as in <hi>death</hi> (we heard) <hi>ſin</hi> loſt its being, ſo at the reſurrection <hi>death</hi> and the <hi>grave</hi> ſhall forever loſe theirs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it ſhall be deſtroyed, ver.</hi> 26. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be ſwallowed up, In the 54. ver. immediately preceding the Text, to which the Apoſtle relates in theſe words, <hi>O death where is thy ſting?</hi> &amp;c. which he ſpeaks by way of <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation</hi> of faith, and (according as before I expreſſed it) as it were before hand tuning his voice, that he might ſing them out aloud in that laſt great <hi>Jubile,</hi> and then <hi>death and the grave</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 13</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall give up their dead,</hi> and diſgorge themſelves of all that they had before ſwallowed, and then not onely the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170050:55"/> 
                  <hi>ſting of death,</hi> but alſo <hi>death</hi> it ſelfe ſhall <hi>die</hi> and ceaſe for ever, <hi>for there ſhall then be no more death,</hi> then our<note place="margin">Rev. 21. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>dead bodies</hi> ſhall again <hi>live, Iſa.</hi> 26. 19. ſo as thenceforth they <hi>can die no more, Luke</hi> 20. 36. but what is ſaid of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſhall then be made good of his <hi>ſervants,</hi> they ſhall then <hi>live who were dead, and ſhall live for ever, Rev.</hi> 1. 18. and then <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> as van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed enemies ſhall bee dragged after our glorious <hi>Conquerurs</hi> Charet, whileſt his <hi>Redeemed ones</hi> ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him with their joyful and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acclamations, and make Heaven and Earth eccho this triumphant ſong <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> Nor will they forget to adde that which the Apoſtle doeth, <hi>v. 57. Now thanks be to God, who hath given us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Which fitly leads me to the <hi>Application.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ANd let the firſt be everlaſting <note place="margin">SERM. III</note> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Praiſe and thankſgiving to the <hi>Prince of our peace, and captain of our ſalvation.</hi> Now and ever bleſſed be our <hi>God, who hath given us the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 57.</note> 
                  <hi>through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170050:55"/> and truly it muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a moſt <hi>free gift</hi> if we have it, for did we fight and win it, that we ſhould wear it? No, <hi>he tred the wine-preſſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 1, 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>alone, and of the people there was none with him when he came from</hi> Edom <hi>with his garments died in the blood of theſe our enemies, travelling in the greatneſſe of his ſtrength, mighty to ſave,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Theophylact</hi> upon the Text. He endured the conflict, and in and by him gained the victory; or as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expreſſeth it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ille pugna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſuſtinuit, nos coronis &amp; trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis ſuis ornavit.</hi> P. Martyr. Rev. 4. 10, 11. Ezek. 21. 26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>He got the victory, and let us wear the Crown.</hi> But ſhall not then humble and thankful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity <hi>caſt down our Crowns at his feet,</hi> or rather ſet them on his head, <hi>whoſe right it is?</hi> and ſay, thou art <hi>worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, and honour, and power, for thou haſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they are, and were created;</hi> all is by him, and from him, and therefore let the praiſe of all be to him for ever. It was,</p>
               <p>1. His <hi>death,</hi> which gave death its deadly wound, and by <hi>death be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him who had the power of death</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 14.</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170050:56"/> 
                  <hi>which is the Devil.</hi> And this</p>
               <p>As moſt <hi>gloriouſly,</hi> whileſt thus in his greateſt <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> he foileth Satan in his greateſt ſtrength, <hi>vincit dum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 4</note> 
                  <hi>vincitur,</hi> when as a weak man he is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome of death, as the mighty, Almighty God hee overcometh both death, and him that had the power of it, and on the very Croſſe <hi>made a ſhew</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2. 15. <hi>Muſculus.</hi> Rom. 6. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>of him openly,</hi> when he himſelf was there <hi>made a ſpectacle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So moſt <hi>juſtly;</hi> for ſeeing <hi>death is the wages onely of ſinne,</hi> he moſt righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forfeited that his <hi>power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> by inflicting <hi>death on him who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor, 5. 21</note> 
                  <hi>knew no ſin;</hi> and thus <hi>Jeroboams</hi> arm<note place="margin">1 Kin. 13. 4 <hi>In Epitaph: Nepot. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Hydrus Crocodilum interficit. P. Dammian: li. 2. ep. 18. Dentes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringes in nimis ſolido: concoquere non poteris, ſed ſicut Danielis bolo Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, eruciabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; crepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi> Del Rio Adagial. pag. 250.</note> drieth up, when ſtretched out to lay hold on Gods Prophet; and the waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh angry <hi>Bee</hi> faſtening her ſting where ſhee ſhould not, hath loſt both it and her life together. This made <hi>Hierom</hi> inſult over death, <hi>illius morte tu mortua es, devoraſti &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orata es;</hi> but withall he bleſſeth Chriſt for it, <hi>Gratias tibi Chriſte Salvator, quod tam potentem adverſarium noſtrum, dum occideris, occidiſti,</hi> its moſt juſt that death ſhould die, for ſeiſing on the Lord of Life, who never deſerved it; and although we did, yet juſt too,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170050:56"/> that we ſhould be delivered, ſeeing our <hi>Surety</hi> hath ſatisfied. And thus our bleſſed <hi>Redeemer,</hi> by being lifted up on the Croſſe, fought with theſe our enemies from the higher ground, and ſo mortally wounded their head; and that ſpear which pierced his heart brake this ſtring, which elſe would have wounded ours; <hi>in hoc ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vinces;</hi> ſo that however other Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are wont to be diſmaied at the death of their Captains, yet we are delivered, and ſo animated by the death of ours; his death is our life, &amp; therefore let him have that praiſe, which he purchaſed at ſo dear a price.</p>
               <p>2. His <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is both the cauſe and pledge of ours, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 20, 21. hath a ſpeciall influence into our <hi>juſtification, Rom.</hi> 4. 25. &amp; 8. 34. affording faith (by <hi>which we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified</hi>)<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> a ſure handhold; in that it clearly manifeſteth, that he had paid the debt, when the priſoner was ſet free, ſatisfied Gods Juſtice, when the arreſt of death was taken off, and then, <hi>O death where i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſting?</hi> and by opening his own grave, had done as much for ours, and then, <hi>O grave,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 37. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170050:57"/>
               <p>3. The imputation <hi>of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, death, and unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> is that which in our juſtification takes off Gods revenging wrath, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning guilt of ſin, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> our Apoſtle ſaith, is the <hi>ſting of death,</hi> and ſo he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us <hi>from going down into the pit,</hi> or at leaſt bringeth us up out of it, <hi>becauſe he hath found a ranſome, Job.</hi> 33. 24.</p>
               <p>4. It is the <hi>grace of his Spirit,</hi> by which we are enabled to mortifie the the deeds and luſts of the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. which was another ſting of ſin, and ſo of death, which the finger of the Spirit of Chriſt only take's out.</p>
               <p>It is not our ſtrongeſt purpoſes or reſolutions that will be able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter theſe enemies; a foul ſore, til it be indeed healed, will run, though we ſay it ſhall not.</p>
               <p>Nor will the Heathens, and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers <hi>Purgative virtues,</hi> cleanſe this ſink, in which the beſt of them ſo foully wallowed.</p>
               <p>Nor the Papiſts Purgatories, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, watchings, whippings, louſie ſhirts, or S. <hi>Francis</hi> his kisſing<note place="margin">Bonavent. in ejus vita cap. 2.</note> or licking of Lepers ſores, which will cleanſe this fretting leproſie. The poor woman in the goſpel after
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170050:57"/> ſhe had ſpent all ſhe had on other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Phyſicians, could not get her<note place="margin">Mark 5. 25. 26, 27.</note> iſſue of blood ſtopped, till ſhe got a touch of Chriſts garment. <hi>Porphyric</hi> himſelf confeſſeth that nothing elſe can effect this cleanſing, <hi>ſola principia</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Morn: de veritat. Rel. cap. 27</note> 
                  <hi>hanc purgation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perficere poſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> By w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                  <hi>Principia</hi> ſome conceive, were meant the 3 <hi>Perſons</hi> in the bleſſed <hi>Trinity;</hi> but whatſoever he meant by them, I am ſure it was the <hi>blood</hi> of the ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Lev. 14. 14. 15, 16.</note> and the <hi>oil</hi> that cleanſeth the <hi>Leper</hi> in the Law, and that by them was meant the blood of Chriſt, and the grace of his Spirit which alone hath power to cleanſe and heal both them then, and us now under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>5. They are alſo the conſolations and comforts of the ſame Spirit of Chriſt, which are the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>Lenitives,</hi> which actually &amp; formally take away all that pain and anguiſh, which the ſting of ſin and death make<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 22. Rom. 14. 17.</note> in our conſciences, ſuch <hi>joy and peace are fruits of this ſpirit,</hi> and ſpring from no other root. It is the Lord<note place="margin">Joh. 10. 11. See <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> on Gen. 25. 2.</note> Jeſus who is our <hi>good Shepherd,</hi> and as it is the good Shepherds work and office, firſt to feed his ſheep, and then ſecondly, to make them lie down and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170050:58"/> reſt, ſo he onely doeth both theſe to our ſouls, <hi>feedeth us in green paſtures,</hi> Pſal. 23. 2. <hi>and makes us lie down at noon,</hi> yea, and at night too, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 7. the firſt in our life time, and the other event in death, and thence no ſting in death to a good Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>6. Finally, it will be his laſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing, at the bright luſtre whereof the ſhadow of death will then quite vaniſh, and death it ſelf (which till then had continued and prevailed, and juſt then having cut down all before it, had (as it were) completed its conqueſt) ſhall then for ever be ſwallowed up in victory.</p>
               <p>And thus we ſee our Chriſt, who is our <hi>all,</hi> from firſt to laſt in this<note place="margin">Col. 3. 11.</note> great atchievement of our victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver death, put down all, and therefore to him moſt deſervedly let be all the praiſe; and if the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> when<note place="margin">Judg. 16. 23, 24.</note> they had gotten <hi>Samſon</hi> into their power, <hi>praiſed their Gods, and offered a great ſacrifice to</hi> Dagon, <hi>and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that he had delivered their enemy into their hands, who had deſtroyed their Country, and ſlain many of them;</hi> then <hi>what Lebanon is ſufficient to burn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 16. Pſa. 50. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>or what cattell on a thouſand kills ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170050:58"/> for a burnt ſacrifice?</hi> what <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catombs</hi> of praiſe and ſervice, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are, have, can doe or ſuffer, are due to our great God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? who hath delivered the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our both bodies and ſouls into our hands, and us out of his; who hath ſlaine not onely <hi>many</hi> of us, but either hath or will make havock of us all, <hi>heaps upon heaps,</hi> farre more and greater then ever <hi>Samſon</hi> did of<note place="margin">Judg. 15. 16. Aſa. 115. 1.</note> them. Now <hi>not unto us, not unto us, O Lord,</hi> but to our moſt mighty and moſt mercifull God and Saviour, be all the praiſe, who hath thus <hi>delivered us from the power of darkneſſe, and hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 13 Davenant in locum.</note> 
                  <hi>tranſlated</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>i. e.</hi> hath as a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, tranſplanted us into a new and better Country) from under the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of ſin and death <hi>into the kingdome of his dear Son;</hi> the Lord of life and glory, hath opened for us that <hi>iron</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jude 6. Heb. 7. 16.</note> gate, and broken thoſe everlaſting chaines of darkneſſe aſunder and, having perfectly vanquiſhed hell and death, hath inſtated <hi>us in that power of an endleſſe life.</hi> Now glory to God on high, and on earth peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> For as this matter of his end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe praiſe, ſo of <hi>ſtrong and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170050:59"/> conſolation and good hope</hi> to<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 16. Heb. 6. 18.</note> all thoſe that are made partakers of <hi>the grace of life.</hi> For ſo <hi>Calvin</hi> right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerveth, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here in the Text, <hi>tam animos â exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione erigere voluit Corinthiorum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos;</hi> by ſuch an hearty and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant exclamation as this, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi> He intended to rouze and raiſe up the drooping, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, ſinking hearts of Believers, and by this <hi>Proſopopoeia,</hi> (as <hi>P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proponit ob oculos mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foſſam.</note> adde's) he preſenteth death as having got a deadly wound, and now lying proſtrate at their feet, for them ſecurely to trample upon, and to triumph over, the ſting being gone, and the honey onely remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whileſt it hath delivered them from their worſt enemy, ſin; and more nearly united them to their beſt friend Jeſus Chriſt their Lord and Head. It doth indeed part them from the bodily preſence of other deareſt relations here on earth, and from their bodies too, which they muſt leave alſo for a time, till they at laſt come to a more joyful meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But not from God, who
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170050:59"/> as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan, in death are</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 23. <hi>Bernard in Cant. Serm</hi> 26.</note> 
                  <hi>not parted.</hi> So that what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>porta inferni,</hi> is now <hi>introitus regni,</hi> the gate of Hell is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the entrance into Heaven; or as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>what was before the Devils Serjeant to drag us to Hell, is now the Lords Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher to conduct us to Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 31. 8. dying men are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>phraſe</hi> which hath trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled<note place="margin">Vide Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
                  <hi>Interpreters,</hi> to give the true ſenſe of it; the word uſually ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a <hi>change of raiment,</hi> and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed death ſtrip's us all, but happy they whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſpread his skirt over, they then will not bee <hi>found naked, but clothed upon with their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3, 4,</note> 
                  <hi>houſe from Heaven.</hi> This a Believer hath in death, yea by death, and what concluſion then ſhould he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre from it, but the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go?<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 8, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore my heart is glad, and my glory rejoiceth, my fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope, becauſe thou wilt not leave my ſoul in Hell, but wilt ſhew me the path of life, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore I will not onely reſt in peace, but leap for joy, whileſt I can thus inſult over ſo deadly an enemy; the <hi>righteous may
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170050:60"/> well have hope in their death,</hi> when<note place="margin">Prov. 14. 32.</note> from this Text, they may be ſure of the victory.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Which therefore ſhould arm the heirs of life againſt the fear of death; we read, <hi>Cant. 3. 7, 8. that the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant of Iſrael have their ſwords on their thighs, becauſe of fear in the night;</hi> which implieth, that as<note place="margin">So the <hi>Greeks,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their many words for a night have <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for one which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports fear.</note> other nights uſually ſtrike men (at leaſt children) into fears, ſo this long and more darkſome night of death, is ſubject to raiſe fears even in thoſe that are <hi>men of God.</hi> Eſpecially whileſt they are weak children, they are oft weary of life, and yet afraid of death, that God (in a manner) knoweth not what to do with them; as the Angel (<hi>in Cyprian</hi>) chideth ſuch, <hi>pati timetis, exire non vultis, quid faciam vobis?</hi> and truly ſuch children ſhould be chid out of ſuch childiſh fears, but from the <hi>valiant of Iſrael</hi> God expecteth more ſpirit, if not wholly to prevent ſuch inſults, yet with courages to repel them; for elſe to what purpoſe ſerve <hi>their ſwords on their thighs?</hi> and a lively faith in their hearts, if the fears of death can dead it? It is a ſad word
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170050:60"/> of <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14, 15. <hi>He</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Si quis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pacare non poteſt mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptu, is ſciat p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um ſe adhuc profeciſſe in Chriſti fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ut nimia tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidatio ex ignorantia Chriſti gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae naſcitur, ita certum eſt infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note> 
                  <hi>that cannot quiet his heart in all holy contempt of death, let him know that he hath as yet profited but a very little in the faith of Chriſt, becauſe this trembling ariſeth from too much igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his grace, and is a certain ſign of too much infidelity:</hi> For ſo <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10. 7. affirmeth, that doubtingly to ask, <hi>who ſhall deſcend into the deep? is to bring Chriſt again from the dead,</hi> as though he had not died, and by his death overcome death and Hell: but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</p>
               <p>1. The example of Chriſt our Saviour dying, ſhould animate eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian Souldier againſt fears of death; his taſting of it for us,<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 9.</note> ſhould keep it from being to us a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of trembling: for if the weak ſilly ſheep freely followeth, where the <hi>dux gregis,</hi> before hath led the way, why ſhould the ſheep of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Paſture be at a ſtand, though it be in the valley of the ſhadow of death, from <hi>following the Lamb whither ſoever</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>he goeth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. But the merit and efficacy of the death of Chriſt ſhould in this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170050:61"/> kinde be moſt operative; as it paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the wrath, ſatisfieth the juſtice of God, removeth guilt, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth<note place="margin">Maledictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndo ſuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit quod in morte for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midabile erat. <hi>Cypr.</hi>
                  </note> life; had we the skill of faith to apply it aright to our wounded ſouls, it would be able ſo perfectly to take out the ſting of death, that we ſhould have no cauſe to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the fear of it; for ſo it is <hi>ſignanter dictum,</hi> by <hi>death he hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14, 15.</note> deſtroyed him who had the power of <hi>death,</hi> ſo as to deliver them that were all their life time in bondage, by reaſon of their fear of it: ſo that if we ſhall fear, it is ſome bodies fault, it is none of his; for on his part <hi>activè, quoad cauſam &amp; funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> (and in the ſenſe that <hi>fear</hi> is ſometimes taken for the thing fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) we are delivered from the fear of death.</p>
               <p>Though on our part, through weakneſſe of faith, or want of due exerciſe of it, <hi>paſſivè, quoad effectum vel eventum,</hi> we may be too much diſturbed with this paſſion, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly fear it; as a man before in danger, if now by his friend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſet in ſafety, we may truly ſay he is put out of fear, though for his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170050:61"/> part (as not ſenſible of it) you may poſſibly ſee him yet ſtand quaking and trembling, like him who after a ſtorm which he hath been in, is now ſafe on the ſhore, and yet his head is ſo dizzy and turns round, that he think's he is ſtill rowling and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the tempeſt.</p>
               <p>But ſhall we be ſo ſilly, that when Chriſt hath knockt off our chains, the Devil through theſe fears ſhould tie and keep us bound with ſtraws?</p>
               <p>Nay, ſhall we be ſo unkind (I had almoſt ſaid, ſo prophane) as with <hi>Ahaz, Iſa.</hi> 7. in ſuch a trembling fit as you read of <hi>v.</hi> 2. not only <hi>to weary men, but God alſo,</hi> v. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not only be injurious to our own peace and life, but alſo to the worth and efficacy of Chriſts death, as though it were not able to fetch out the ſting, and all the poiſon of ours.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially ſeeing that after his <hi>death</hi> followed his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> thoſe<note place="margin">Act. 2. 24.</note> chains of death being too weak to hold him, but that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>exceeding greatneſſe of his mighty</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 19. Judg. 16. 9 12.</note> 
                  <hi>power Samſon</hi>-like eaſily ſnapt them, as ſo many burnt threeds aſunder,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170050:62"/> and ſo <hi>diſruptis mortis, ſepulchri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferni repagulis,</hi> he riſeth in the glory of that his might as a Conquerour over death, and ſo <hi>dieth no more,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 9.</note> that we might fear no more. <hi>Death hath no more dominion over him,</hi> that the terrour of it may have none over us. Thus our <hi>Eliſha</hi> hath caſt that<note place="margin">2 King. 2. 21.</note> ſalt into theſe bitter waters, and ſo healed them, that from thenceforth there might be no death in them; and although there were ſometimes <hi>death in the pot,</hi> and a deadly poiſonous ſting in that death, yet by caſting in of this <hi>meale,</hi> there is now no <hi>harm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 4. 40, 41.</note> but meat and medicine, life and ſtrength in it; and how long then ſhall we be ſo weak as like children to be afraid of our Phyſician and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick? Or like ſuch timorous men, who, when in the dark, are afraid of any thing they ſee, thinking it to be a Devil, or an enemy, which when it come's near, proves their very friend? But when ſhall we once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to that <hi>boldneſſe of faith</hi> as not to<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 13.</note> fear death, which by the death and reſurrection of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is become a Serpent without a ſting, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though an enemy, yet ſuch an one as
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170050:62"/> hath loſt the victorie?</p>
               <p>The way to our help herein, will<note place="margin">Helps a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fear of death.</note> be</p>
               <p>1. To enquire into the occaſions and cauſes of this our malady; and then</p>
               <p>2. To apply to each their ſeveral proper remedies, that ſo although we muſt all die, yet we may die in peace; and whereas ſome ſay, that all die of a Feaver, yet we may not in a cold ſhaking fit, but with ſuch peace, comfort, joy, and triumph, that we may then ſay <hi>Pauls</hi> words, with <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit and faith, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Now amongſt thoſe cauſes of<note place="margin">Cauſes of this fear.</note> our fear of death, ſome may be more blameleſſe and excuſable, if not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, for a true believer (and that as acting faith) may lawfully in ſome caſes deſire the continuance of life, and ſo far in a regular way and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure fear death.</p>
               <p>1. From a natural averſation from death, if not as a fruit of ſin, yet as an enemy and deſtroyer of nature, which before I hinted was in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> yea, in Chriſt himſelf; as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170050:63"/> appeared in his agony and bloody<note place="margin">Lu. 22. 44.</note> ſweat, in that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, being amazed, and very heavy, and his ſoul being exceeding ſorrowful unto death, <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 33, 34. ſo that again and again he prayeth the ſame words, <hi>v.</hi> 39. that if it were poſſible that Cup might paſſe from him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 39. I confeſſe there was more bitterneſſe in that Cup, then of a bare natural, or a more ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry violent death, but yet death as it is in it ſelf a privation of life, and ſo a natural evil; ſo it was no ſin in our Saviour in way of natural affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to turn from it, but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his obedience to ſubject himſelf, and his natural deſires and<note place="margin">Matth. 26. 42. Mark 14. 36.</note> fears to his Fathers will in it.</p>
               <p>2. From ſome more ſpeciall grounds of deſire of continuance of life:</p>
               <p>As, till he attain ſome mercy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> deſireth to live to go over <hi>Iordan,</hi> and ſee that goodly Mountain and Lebanon, <hi>Deut.</hi> 3. 25. and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> weeps <note n="*" place="margin">When he heareth he muſt die before he had an heir. Iſa. 28. 3.</note>.</p>
               <p>Or ſome mercy promiſed, as no doubt <hi>Simeon</hi> could not have been willing to ſee death, till (as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170050:63"/> to him) he had ſeen the Lords Chriſt, though then he deſired to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 26, 28, 29, 30.</p>
               <p>Or till he effect and accompliſh ſome work and ſervice which God hath called and fitted him unto; ſo the Pſalmiſt deſireth to live to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate Gods praiſe, <hi>Pſalm 119. 17. 5. Pſalm</hi> 71. 18. as a true la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer will deſire his day may laſt, till his work be done; but in theſe and the like particulars, there is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a deſire of life then fear of death, though where there is a true deſire of any thing, the fear of the contrary to it muſt needs bee proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>3. In ſome other reſpects there may be more formal fears of death, and yet leſſe ſinful, and more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable.</p>
               <p>As in general, by reaſon of the greatneſſe of that <hi>change</hi> and <hi>task,</hi> which in death every man, the beſt <hi>Saint,</hi> is brought to and put upon.</p>
               <p>For ſo, <hi>All changes</hi> uſually affect us; let it be but the turning of the blood, (as they uſe to call it) after the opening of a vein, the man is oft at a ſwooning fit.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170050:64"/>
               <p>But as all <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> is awful, ſo<note place="margin">Ezek. 1. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>great tasks</hi> are wont to make us very thoughtful and ſollicitous; and <hi>great changes</hi> uſe greatly to affect us, and therefore the great change at the laſt day will <hi>make even the powers of Heaven to ſhake, Matth.</hi> 24. 29. by which ſome underſtand the Angels of Heaven, though they be ſafe enough: ſo proportionably the day of our death being the day of our particular doom, in which we have one of our laſt and greateſt changes to be undergone, and one of our moſt important tasks to be ſet upon and gone through with. Wonder not if you ſhould then ſee the wary, buſie, thoughtful, carefull ſoul trembling: as for inſtance,</p>
               <p>The parting of the ſoul and body, ſo nearly united, and ſo long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, and never yet ſevered, is a very hard twitch.</p>
               <p>The leaving of this world of men, to goe now into the world of ſouls, into that farre ſtrange Country, is a great change.</p>
               <p>The pains and pangs of death with ſome are very ſtrong, ſo that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly you have ſometimes ſeen ſome
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170050:64"/> of ſtrong bodies, yea, and faith too, though they had nothing elſe then to doe, yet then finding it a work great enough to be able to die.</p>
               <p>Our laſt accounts are, then to be given up, <hi>Eccleſ. 12. 7. Luke</hi> 16. 2. and that is a very awfull buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>And this to a moſt glorious Lord and Judge, whom we are then to appear before, and if here we find a dread Majeſty in his very ſmiles, when he is on a mercy-ſeat, now that he is on the Judgment ſeat, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence cannot but be very dreadful.</p>
               <p>Remembrance of former ſins, though pardoned, may make the dying mans pale cheeks bluſh.</p>
               <p>And ſenſe of preſent defilement and weakneſſe, though now dying with him, may make the pure in heart ſhrink back from appearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo pure an eye.</p>
               <p>And thoſe laſt conflicts with the world, ſin, and Satan, are oft then moſt fierce and violent, and unleſſe the Sun of righteouſneſſe do then more gloriouſly ſhine out upon us with his more enlightening and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livening beams in this chill and gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhadow of death, even the man of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170050:65"/> God may tremble, and yet all this, in theſe and the like caſes, but as an <hi>Iſaacs trembling,</hi> Gen. 27. 33. or a <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>quaking,</hi> Heb. 12. 21. Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential, holy, comfortable, and more <hi>awfull</hi> then <hi>fearfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. But farther then God helpeth and ſtrengtheneth, the beſt of us may then be ſubject to worſe and more ſinfull fears; ſome of the cauſes wherof may be theſe, to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I ſhall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſubjoin their cures &amp; remedies.</p>
               <p>1. Firſt, a more generall cauſe of this fear of death, is a ſecure careleſſe neglect ſeriouſly beforehand to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of it, and accordingly to prepare for it in time of life, for ſo by comming ſuddenly and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly, it puts all on heaps and confuſion. So <hi>ſuddenneſſe</hi> and <hi>fear</hi>
                  <note place="margin">for 5. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> in other caſes are joined together, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 25. and <hi>ſuddenneſſe of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> coming upon any, is a deſcription of a moſt carefull and dolefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 3. it is ſo here, when in our life time we have not taken a due and timely eſtimate of the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents, concomitants, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of death, of all the evil that is in it, and ſo have laid in no provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170050:65"/> of thoſe cordialls and comforts that ſhould antidote and ſweeten it, before we are aware of it, or prepared for it, to <hi>taſt</hi> of it, rendreth it that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>cup of trembling,</hi> the<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 9. Zech. 12. 2</note> man unawares hath ſet his feet on a Bog, and he and it tremble, and quake, and ſink together, like <hi>Nabal,</hi> whoſe heart died before he did, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 37.</p>
               <p>And therefore the Prophylactick here is a frequent and thoughtful me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of it, and a dayly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able preparation for it, and ſo, when it commeth, it prove's leſſe terrible. Whatever the Philoſophers meant by defining their <hi>Philoſophy</hi> to be a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation</hi> of their Metaphorical <hi>death,</hi> I am ſure that in plain terms the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and ſerious meditating of this death, we now ſpeak of, is a great part of true ſaving Chriſtian <hi>Divinity;</hi> and if with <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea,</hi> we<note place="margin">John 19. 41.</note> would have our Sepulchres, in our Gardens, if thoughts of <hi>death</hi> did oft recurr in our beſt <hi>life,</hi> eſpecially if in every ſickneſſe, diſeaſe, and danger, in which God <hi>knock's</hi> at our door,<note place="margin">Luke 12. 36.</note> and tell's us that he is coming, wee could more <hi>livelily</hi> ſee <hi>deaths</hi> face, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170050:66"/> ſo grow more acquainted with it, (as Souldiers are wont) we ſhould at laſt be leſſe afraid of it. <hi>I proteſt by your rejoycing in Chriſt Jeſus, I die daily,</hi> ſaith our apoſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 31. of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; a daily dying, is joyned with a laſt days rejoycing, and our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual <hi>putting our lives into our hands,</hi> as<note place="margin">Judg. 12. 3. Pſal. 119. 109.</note> ready to offer them up to God, will be a means willingly to part with them, when God ſhall pleaſe to call for them; a dying before hand <hi>in thought</hi> will make <hi>dying indeed</hi> leſſe troubleſom: for how forcible and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual would forethoughts of death be to make us to fear to ſin, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not to fear to die? whileſt the eye of Faith hath before taken view of death, in all the evil that any way is in it, and of all that good which to a believer cometh by it.</p>
               <p>But ſo, as this meditation be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with an anſwerable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, for otherwiſe as <hi>Solomon</hi> in another caſe ſaith, he that <hi>increaſeth knowledge increaſeth ſorrow, Ecleſ.</hi> 1. 18. ſo here the more I <hi>know,</hi> the more I <hi>fear,</hi> and <hi>grieve,</hi> whileſt I know ſo much evil in it, which then abides me, and withal that all that good which
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170050:66"/> may be in it, I, for my part, ſhall fall ſhort of. With how much ſhaking doth the unripe apple fall off, when a ripe one drops down without that trouble? the Vine weepeth, when <hi>the branch is cut off before the harveſt, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 18. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſowre grape is but yet ripening in the flowre;</hi> but with what harveſt joy ſhall we come to the <hi>grave, when we ſhall be like a ſhock of ripe corn, which commeth in in his ſeaſon?</hi> Job 5. 26. to which for a cloſe of this, let me adde what there followeth, <hi>Lo this, we have</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>ſearched it, ſo it is, and therefore hear and know it for your good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. And becauſe in this preparation for death, praier is one ſpecial part of it; therefore the neglect of prayer is one great cauſe of the anguiſh and and fear of it; and ſo we finde that want of prayer is joyned with want of hope at ſuch a time in the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit, <hi>Job</hi> 27. 8. with 9. 10. they that uſe not to look up to God to <hi>ſeek</hi> him before, will then hardly <hi>finde him;</hi> and then for the <hi>child</hi> in that dark entry, not to have the <hi>Father</hi> by the hand wil be very terrible: the true children of God may poſſibly be more to ſeek for their comfort at their deaths, by
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170050:67"/> reaſon of their leſſe ſeeking it in their lives, in that it oft falleth out, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their many and earn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uits for grace to carry them on in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir way, they have not been ſo mindful as they ſhould to beg for a ſmile in their Journeies end, which God make's account, is a mercy worth asking, and therefore we <hi>receive not</hi> becauſe we <hi>ask not Jam.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
               <p>For remedy therefore, <hi>ask that you may have,</hi> now <hi>ſeek, that you may then finde,</hi> and all your <hi>life time be knocking</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 7</note> 
                  <hi>hard at the gate of mercy,</hi> that at your out-gate of this life <hi>an abundant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>may be adminiſtred unto you; into the everlaſting kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Have you ordinarily known the man, who was much in prayer while he lived, to be full of fears and anguiſh when he came die? No, thoſe ſweet and ſtrong breathings blow away ſuch darkſome clouds, and therby the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sunne ſhineth out brightly. For prayer,</p>
               <p>1. Through mercy procure's it, it can get any good thing, at a good Gods hand, and why not comfort in death? nay, then eſpecially, for then
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170050:67"/> begin's a believers harveſt, when he re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s the fruit of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Job 5. 26. Revel. 14. 15.</note> and hath oftentimes a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> return of all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which before (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y be) he thought God, as well as himſelf, had forgotten.</p>
               <p>2. As prayer thus impetrate's it, ſo it naturally (as it were) trains us up to it; for by conſtant acquaintance <hi>with prayer,</hi> we come to more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar acquaintance <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> and ſo come to ſee and feel how happy it is to be near him, which cannot but make us the more ready and deſirous of getting out of the body,<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23. 2 Cor. 5. 6.</note> that we may be no longer abſent from him; and beſides, the happy ſoul, which, with the ſweet bird is continually ſoaring upward, and keepeth much aloft, is ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe approaches to Heaven, that now when it fitteth on the dying mans lips, it is ready on the wing to take its laſt flight, as in that dark night very well knowing its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed way thither, and having ſo often ſent its prayers, thoſe winged meſſengers, thither before-hand, now with joy and ſinging mounteth up it
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170050:68"/> ſelf thither, and therefore be much in prayer now, if in death you would have an anſwer of peace.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Falſe heartedneſſe</hi> is another cauſe of <hi>faint-heartedneſſe,</hi> in theſe <hi>animae deliquia,</hi> the rotten quagmire quakes and ſinks when trod on; and ſo <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> (we read) <hi>ſurprizeth hypocrites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 33. 14.</note> when death and danger layeth hold on them, God then takes away their <hi>ſouls</hi> and their <hi>hopes</hi> together, <hi>Job</hi> 27. 8. as elſe where their hope is ſaid to be as the <hi>giving up of the ghoſt.</hi> Miſerable<note place="margin">cap. 11. 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> man! if thy ſoul and thy hope goe out with the breath of the ſame dying groan.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, (by way of remedy) <hi>Hezekiahs walking before God perfectly, and with an upright heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 3.</note> was the beſt ſtake in his hedge, when the newes of death made all crack; and ſo much truth &amp; ſincerity as we have, juſt ſo much peace &amp; comfort ſhall we have in dangers &amp; death, and no more. The <hi>Heathens</hi> under their Fables of <hi>Minos, Aeacus, &amp; Rhadamanthus,</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Plato in Gorgia. Hora mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, hora ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itatis.</note> to us, that at death there will be a ſtrict Scrutiny, and however in our life time we have been judged by our ſelves and others with our cloths on,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170050:68"/> yet then we ſhall all be judged naked, then all vizards will be laid aſide, all black patches and beauty ſpots that covered foul ſores will be <hi>pluckt,</hi> off &amp; the pure heart only will be able to <hi>lift up their face without ſpot, and be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 11. 15</note> 
                  <hi>and not fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>Too much love of the world</hi> is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great cauſe of our <hi>as much fear of death,</hi> when we are to leave it, for fear ever preſuppoſeth love, and ſo much as I love any thing, ſo much I am ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved &amp; afraid to part w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it; with what crying is the child pluckt from the breaſt, when it hath taſted of the ſweetneſſe of it, and as yet skill's of no other nouriſhment? things faſt glued together, are torn &amp; broken when vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently pluckt aſunder, &amp; if thy cloth cleave to thy skin, as it is a ſigne that there is ſome ſore under it, ſo it will make all ſmart when pluckt off, and anſwerably if thy portion (with them <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 14.) be in this life, thou art utterly undone, when it is ended: <hi>Job</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 29. 13</note> ſome-where ſpeaks of <hi>dying in his neſt,</hi> but as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerveth, <hi>Neſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> are wont to be but <hi>weaklins,</hi> and they that have feathered their neſts in the world, have minde to be on the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170050:69"/> wing to flie out of it, <hi>O death, how bitter is thy remembrance to him that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecclus. 41. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>liveth at eaſe in his poſſeſſions?</hi> how ſad a ſight is the <hi>hand-writing on the wall</hi> to a <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in his cups? and when<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> the rich man is dreaming of <hi>goods laid up for many years,</hi> how dreadfull a ſound in his ears was that, <hi>Thou fool,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12. 12, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>this night, &amp;c?</hi> when in proſperity the deſtroyer cometh upon him, <hi>Job</hi> 15. 21. It was a wiſe and Chriſtian ſpeech of <hi>Charles the</hi> 5t. to the <hi>Duke of Venice,</hi> who when he had ſhewn him the glory of his Princely Palace and Earthly Paradiſe, inſtead of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it, or him for it, onely return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him this grave and ſerious <hi>memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Haec ſunt quae faciunt invitos mori:</hi> theſe are the things which make us unwilling to die, and ſo ſharpen deaths ſting, and make it more pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; it is a double death to him who is alive to the world, to part with it.</p>
               <p>Whereas on the contrary (again for the remedy) if with <hi>Paul</hi> we were before hand <hi>crucified to the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and had it crucified to us,</hi> and (as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> deſcan'ts upon the place) lay like two dead bodies one by another, as there was no mutual deſire, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170050:69"/> in each other, when they lay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſo there would be as little grief when they are parted aſunder, the world not caring for us, and we as little for it, and ſo by our parting no hurt done; were we indeed ſtrangers and pilgrims here, we would not go home weeping; were we and the world <hi>two,</hi> at our parting there would not be a painful <hi>diſſolutio continui,</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting looſe now, would prevent ſuch convulſion fits, and rentings then.</p>
               <p>5. On the contrary, <hi>too much care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of the things of this world,</hi> makes ſome mens deaths more careful, and themſelves more fearful.</p>
               <p>In particular, (I mean) our neglect of a provident and timely <hi>ſetting our houſe in order</hi> when we are now lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the world, is apt to leave us in heaps and confuſion. It is expreſſed in Scripture, as the dying mans task, but<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 1. 2 Sam. 17. 17. 23.</note> it would be much better if it were the living mans care, that when we have made up our <hi>Accounts</hi> with men, we might be more ready for Gods <hi>Audit,</hi> and when we have <hi>diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of our goods to others,</hi> we might be at more leiſure and vacant, the more ſafely to <hi>bequeath our ſouls to God,</hi> &amp; ſo
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170050:70"/> enter upon our heavenly <hi>inheritance;</hi> but it is but our ſin and miſery, that we lay this double burden on the tired horſe-back, that the ending of our <hi>reckonings</hi> with the world, and the beginning of our <hi>accounts</hi> with God, are both put off to be made on a death-bed; and hence commeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens fear of death, the man would not die till his Will be made, and ſo he then ſetteth about it, but it uſually beginning with his <hi>bequeathing of his ſoul to God,</hi> and then this ſad thought commeth in; but upon what acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or grounded aſſurance? which puts the poor man to a ſtop; &amp; the wil is for the preſent laid aſide, and the ſealing of his pardon he then thinks needeth firſt to be looked after, and ſo (it may be) at the laſt, neither of them is effected with comfort; ſuch men being like thoſe who have neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to do their work on the weel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and ſo cannot reſt when the Sabbath com's. but <hi>Heaven</hi> ſets us a better copy to write after; God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving finiſhed his works in ſix dayes,<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 2. Exod. 31. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> reſted and was <hi>refreſhed</hi> on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth; and our Saviour when he had ſaid, it is <hi>finiſhed</hi> then he quietly <hi>gave
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170050:70"/> up the ghoſt,</hi> and ſo reſted in the grave,<note place="margin">John 17. 4. 19, 20.</note> which was typified by the Jewiſh Sabbath. Happy we, if in this work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day of our life, we could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch our greateſt buſineſſe firſt, but yet all our other worldly occaſions alſo in time, that the day of our death may be our Sabbath, in which we may reſt <hi>from our labours,</hi> and <hi>feriari</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 13</note> 
                  <hi>Deo,</hi> even keep a true holy day indeed to God, that then with our Saviour we may ſay, <hi>it is finiſhed</hi> and with <hi>Paul, we have finiſhed our courſe,</hi> and in <hi>running our race,</hi> have outgone all<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7. 8.</note> our griefs and fears, and then may have nothing elſe to do, but onely quietly to take our reſt, and receive the Crown.</p>
               <p>6. But becauſe our apoſtle telleth<note place="margin">V. 56.</note> us, <hi>that the ſting of death is ſin,</hi> and this (as was before expreſſed) both in the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>defilement</hi> of it; they both make death terrible, and us then fearful.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>The guilt of ſin,</hi> if then unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or but ſo apprehended, much terrifieth the conſcience, and ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth death very formidable, whileſt it is looked at as the <hi>wages of ſin,</hi> or<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 13</note> Gods <hi>arreſt,</hi> and ſo the fore-runner or
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170050:71"/> beginning of a more terrible executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and as its <hi>death</hi> to a malefactor to go even out of priſon, if to be brought<note place="margin">So <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is rendred, let him be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> before his Judge, ſo to ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> a <hi>guilty condemned ſinner,</hi> his death is phraſed to be a bringing him to the King of terrors, <hi>Job</hi> 18. 5. with 14. and well it may, when even a beloved child is afraid to come into his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Fathers preſence, when he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; ſome ſuch trouble of ſpirit ſome<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Divines</hi> conceive <hi>Hezekiah</hi> lay under, when he <hi>wept ſo ſore</hi> at the meſſage of death, and <hi>David</hi> alſo when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that reſpite, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 13.</p>
               <p>And therefore our cure here is faith's timely and effectual applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the blood and death of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the only tried cure of this <hi>tremor cordis,</hi> for ſo its expreſly ſaid, that he <hi>by death</hi> hath delivered us<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14, 15.</note> from the bondage of the fear of it. So that the more or leſſe that we are able to apply <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>death,</hi> the more or leſſe we are afraid of our <hi>own;</hi> and hence it is, that</p>
               <p>1. Believers by the clearer diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Chriſt and his death,</hi> under the brighter light of the Goſpel, are leſſe in the dark, in the gloomy ſhadow of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170050:71"/> death, then the faithful under the<note place="margin">See <hi>Calvin</hi> in John 19. 40. Rom. 8. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Law. Their darker vails and ſhadows had leſſe of the ſpirit of <hi>Adoption</hi> and confidence, and more of the <hi>ſpirit of bondage and fear;</hi> as the Apoſtle hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the fore-mentioned place to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> where he ſheweth, that Chriſt by taking <hi>part with the children of fleſh and blood</hi> in his Incarnation, did free us from that bondage, and ſo, whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>giver of the law</hi> deſired to live, <hi>Deu. 3. 24, 25. Paul</hi> a Preacher of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> deſireth to be diſſolved, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. when once the Sun of righteouſneſſe was now more up, yea, <hi>Simeon</hi> crave's leave to depart, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 29. as its firſt riſing.</p>
               <p>2. Hence alſo it is that among ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Believers now under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſuch uſe to be more joyful, and leſſe fearful of death, who by faith have more fully applyed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to whom he hath been moſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and of all ſuch, none more then they that have been moſt humbled, &amp; their hearts moſt broken with ſenſe of ſin, and afterwards have had them more ſoundly healed, and more fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly comforted and enlarged with the aſſurance of <hi>Gods</hi> favour in <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170050:72"/> the bone broken, and well ſet again, proves ſtronger; and the Lute broken if well put together, makes not the worſe but rather the <hi>better muſick.</hi> Of all the Apoſtles, <hi>Paul</hi> at his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in after-ſufferings was moſt humbled, and none of them expreſſe more (none ſo much) cheerful readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deſire to die in Chriſt, yea, to die for him.</p>
               <p>And therefore as our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Mar. 11. 22</note> 
                  <hi>have we faith in God,</hi> oh that we had more, and then could act more faith in God! Could the ſting of a fiery ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent make us daily look more up to the brazen Serpent, ſenſe of ſin drive us more to Chriſt, to get more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of part in his death, wee ſhould thereby (even when <hi>we receive the ſentence of death</hi>) be more able <hi>to truſt in him who quickeneth the dead;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 9.</note> then ſhould we not be pinioned, as condemned Malefactors are wont to be, but have an hand of Faith free and at liberty to lay hold on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Lord of Life, yea, and gladly reach it it out to receive death it ſelf, as that which will more fully unite us to him: when the babe is in its mothers arms, or laid down with a kiſſe, it then ſleep's quietly.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:170050:72"/>
               <p>2. But Secondly, the defilement of ſin, although faith can ſee it pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will make a child-like ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facedneſſe bluſh and fear ſo to come into a Fathers preſence. <hi>My little</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>children,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>abide in him, that when he ſhall appear, we may have confidence, and not be aſhamed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him at his comming;</hi> and although the moſt loving wife heartily deſireth her husbands coming home, yet ſhe could be content that he would ſtay out ſo long, til he have righted things in the houſe, if for the preſent they lie unhandſomely and out of order. With <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah to be lepers to the day of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>our death,</hi> will make a very foul corpſe, and a body fouly diſtemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in life, (eſpecially if the ſoul be found ſo in death) will make death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed-groanes more deadly; ſtrong bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies uſe to have ſtrong pains in death,<note place="margin">John 8. 5. Numb. 25. 8. 2 Sam. 17. 23. &amp; 18. 14. 15. 1 Sam. 28. 7, 8, 9. &amp;c. with 19. Matth 27. 5.</note> and ſo have ſtrong luſts; eſpecially if we be taken <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi</hi> in the very act of uncleanneſſe, <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel</hi> of rebellion; if <hi>Saul</hi> conſult the Divel this day, and go to him the next, and <hi>Judas</hi> by an untimely and woful death, be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly brought before his Judge,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170050:73"/> whileſt he is yet reeking with the blood of his betrayed Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; with what horrour and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt ſuch needs appeare before the Judgement ſeat? <hi>Joſeph,</hi> though<note place="margin">Gen. 41. 14</note> under no ſuch guilt, yet being in the ſqualid condition of a priſoner <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth himſelf and changeth his raiment, when haſtily brought out of the dungeon before Pharaoh,</hi> an infinitely inferiour preſence to that which we at death are to appear before.</p>
               <p>And therefore here again, the death of Chriſt applyed by faith, proveth a Soveraign remedy; for it is then ſafe drawing near to God, when our hearts <hi>are ſprinkled from an evil conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Heb.</hi> 10. 22. and that is by the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14. labour therefore in the way of mortification to be <hi>implanted into Chriſts death,</hi> and<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 5.</note> this ſweet fruit amongſt others, will ſpring out of his grave, that what mortifieth ſin, will kill the fear of death, which is cauſed by it.</p>
               <p>1. Partly as this daily practiſing of dying to ſin, will inure us with more eaſe to die to the world, not onely whileſt we live to be weaned from it, but when God ſhal call, in death wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170050:73"/> to leave it. Luſts are <hi>members Col.</hi> 3. 5. and the content which a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner taketh in them, in his <hi>very life Iſa.</hi> 57. 10. dearer then his natural life, and therefore it is that he is ſo often ready rather deſperately to hazard it, then not to gratifie and ſatisfie them, he therefore who in a courſe of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification hath done the greater, will not ſtick at the leſſe; will not ſtick to part with his dear life, who by the grace of Chriſt hath already parted with his dearer luſt, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual looſing the tie of his ſoul and ſin, he may expect the laſt looſe of his body and ſoul with more comfort.</p>
               <p>2. But mortification effecteth this more directly, in that it properly and formally taketh away ſin which is <hi>fomes morbi,</hi> the very matter of the diſeaſe, and of all theſe ſhaking fits in death, and then as a ſound and well ordered body, dieth with little pain, ſo a ſanctified purged ſoul departeth with leſſe anguiſh; a great deal of grace in our life, brings a great deal of comfort in death; and why ſhould I fear that which at once freeth me from ſin, which in this courſe of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, is the cauſe of my greateſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170050:74"/> grief, and perfect's grace, which is the object of my chiefeſt deſire? what therefore now remaineth, but that we labour to live holily, that we may at laſt die comfortably; and as they were<note place="margin">Acts 9. 37. Luke 23.. 56. Matth. 26. 12.</note> wont to waſh dead bodies, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them for their burial, ſo that we would do as much for our ſouls, get them waſhed in the blood of Chriſt, and daily more and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and embalmed, and perfumed with the graces of his Spirit; So our deaths would not be more <hi>precious</hi> to<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 15.</note> God, then comfortable to our ſelves: So with <hi>Aſa</hi> we ſhould be laid in our graves as <hi>in a bed filled with ſweet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 16. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſpices;</hi> and what the <hi>Romans</hi> were wont to do in their Pageants, at<note place="margin">Herodian: l. 4.</note> the conſecration of their dead Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, would have more realty at our death and Funerals: no Eagle (as with them) to carry the ſoul up to Heaven, but our ſouls as the renewed Eagle would mount up out of ſuch a <hi>bed of ſpices,</hi> to thoſe <hi>mountains of ſpices, where</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 14. <hi>Brightman</hi> Pſal. 16. 11 Matth. 25. 4, 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> O that we were once ſo wiſe, as with thoſe wiſe Virgins to get <hi>oil</hi> enough into our Veſſels, and then our Lamps will burn bright at midnight, in this mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170050:74"/> of death and judgement; when, with them, we ſhall either go to Chriſt, or Chriſt will come to be married to us, and then this ſhall be one ſtrain of our marriage, of our Triumphant Song, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O grave, where is thy victory?</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Tibi Domini Jeſu, qui ſpes es viventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; reſurrectio mortuorum.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
